<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The originall cause of temporall evils. The opinions of the most ancient heathens concerning it, examined by the sacred Scriptures, and referred unto them, as to the sourse and fountaine from whence they sprang. / By Meric Casaubon D.D.</title>
            <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E300_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E300[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The originall cause of temporall evils. The opinions of the most ancient heathens concerning it, examined by the sacred Scriptures, and referred unto them, as to the sourse and fountaine from whence they sprang. / By Meric Casaubon D.D.</title>
                  <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. and are to be sold by Richard Minne, at the signe of S. Paul in Little Britain.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin, Original --  History of doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ORIGINALL CAVSE OF Temporall Evils.</p>
            <p>The opinions of the moſt Ancient Heathens concerning it, examined by the ſacred Scriptures, and referred unto them, as to the Sourſe and Fountaine from whence they ſprang.</p>
            <p>By MERIC CASAUBON D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Orig. <hi>contra</hi> Celſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>IV.</abbr>
               </bibl> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>If any Argument, fit for humane diſquiſition, be of difficult inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to humane induſtry, among ſuch may this which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the</hi> Originall of Evils, <hi>well be reckoned.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Minne,</hi> at the ſigne of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:113190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113190:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſtotle</hi> in his Rhetoricks where he treats of the properties of men according to their ſeverall either ages, or conditions of life, hath a notable obſervation concerning thoſe he properly calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men;</hi> That among a greater number of bad qualities, they have one that is commendable and makes ſome amends; which is, that they are commonly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>lovers of God;</hi> or, <hi>piouſly affected towards God.</hi> It may well ſeeme ſtrange, if not altogether falſe, it being more generally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and apparantly more probable, that <hi>(Bonae mentis ſoror paupertas) Vertue and Poverty</hi> (poverty &amp; piety, the vertue of vertues, eſpecialy) <hi>are of a kind.</hi> It were no hard thing with ſuch diſtinctions and limitations of circumſtances, as in caſes of this nature muſt alwayes be preſuppoſed, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe two. Neither indeed doth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſimply ſay, that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>religious,</hi> in point of life, which may prove quite another thing; but this onely, that ſuch are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:113190:3"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, that <hi>They love God,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther really, or in their opinion onely, is the queſtion: See <hi>S. John</hi> Chap. <hi>XIV.</hi> ver. <hi>15.21, 23, 24.</hi> and the ſame <hi>S. John I.</hi> Epiſt. Chap. <hi>V.</hi> ver. <hi>1, 2, 3.) and have a kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in him,</hi> (or, <hi>truſt in him after a ſort) becauſe of thoſe goods Fortune hath caſt upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is further confirmed by <hi>S. Baſil</hi> alſo (for herein the common ſaying, that <hi>Contrariorum eadem eſt ratio,</hi> will hold well:) where he diſcourſeth of the originall of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme: When men, ſaith he, at firſt are croſſed in their worldly affaires, then begin they, for want of patience, to doubt in themſelves, whether God in very deed regardeth the things of this world; whether he take care of particular men; and whether he reward every man according to his deeds. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards when they ſee no end of their troubles and miſeries, but one evill continually attended with another evill, they ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in themſelves that wicked opinion, and abſolutely reſolve in their hearts, that <hi>there is no God.</hi> So Baſile in his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: That <hi>God is not the cauſe of evils.</hi> The words therefore of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt are very emphaticall,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 44. ver. 9, 10, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt caſt off and put us to ſhame,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All this is come upon us, yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have we dealt falſly in thy covenant. Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113190:3"/>
            <p>At ſuch times then eſpecially, hath that queſtion been moſt rife, (and pertinent indeed) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Whence are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills,</hi> and what brought them forth into the world: of which ſo much hath been written by ancient Philoſophers. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures indeed, not in poſitive aſſertions onely, which in divers places are to be found; but even by the whole ſtreame and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Eccleſiaſticall ſtories and events of all kinds, afford ſo bright and reſplendent a light in this point, that he ſees not the Sun in the firmanent at noon day, who makes not this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from them, That as all evill of ſin is from man, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the Devill; ſo all evill of puniſhment is from God, for the amendment of ſinners. Theſe two, <hi>malum culpae,</hi> and <hi>malum poenae,</hi> (as they are commonly diſcerned,) <hi>the evill of ſin,</hi> and <hi>the evill of puniſhment,</hi> (though this latter be not <hi>evill</hi> abſolutely, but rather <hi>good,</hi> in regard of the end and conſequents of it, as heathens themſelves have well acknowledged:) being the two ſprings, from whence not <hi>Illae,</hi> as it is in the Comick, but <hi>omnes lachrymae;</hi> whatſoever <hi>Adams</hi> wretched poſterity groaneth under, and through which the very frame of this lower and ſublunary world la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth, doth flow. So that were all that profeſſe Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conſequently, to embrace the Scriptures as divine O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, truely and really what they profeſſe; as the reſolution of this point would be eaſie and obvious, ſo the arguing of it, among Christians, needleſſe. But by bookes that of late have been written as well by Proteſtants as by Papiſts, it may
<pb facs="tcp:113190:4"/>eaſily appeare that many among Chriſtians are to be found, who in their inward are nothing leſſe then what outwardly they profeſſe themſelves; yea, and not a few, it ſhould ſeeme, that dare freely enough profeſſe what they beleeve. <hi>Libertins,</hi> as I take it, is their name in ſome countries. And beſides this, it may further appeare by holy <hi>David,</hi> (or whoever was the compoſer of the <hi>73.</hi> Pſal.) that in time of either publick extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary confuſion, or private diſtreſſe and extremity, it may be the caſe of a man, religious otherwiſe and godly, to be at a ſtand for a while, and to entertaine ſome doubts.</p>
            <p>Of all opinions in this kind, contrary to the truth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuctive of all godlineſſe, I find two chiefely to have prevailed in the world. That of <hi>Epicurus</hi> (ſo I call it, becauſe from him chiefely propagated to afterages; though long, in part at leaſt, in the world, before him:) as more knowne, I ſhall firſt name; which was, (as he openly profeſſed it: for ſome ancients make him to have been an arrant atheiſt:) That there is a God, an excellent Nature, whoſe happineſſe and perfection is to injoy himſelf free from all troubles and cares, not regarding or heeding any thing at all but himſelf: That it is a folly to beleeve that God had created the World, as either Sun or Moon, or any other part of this Vniverſe: and not folly alone, but impiety to beleeve that God either regarded what is done by men, or was the cauſe of any whether good or evill that hapneth unto them.</p>
            <p>This opinion, though it might and did in the later ages of
<pb facs="tcp:113190:4"/>the world, when God ceaſed by ſtrange apparitions, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſo familiarly to reveale himſelf unto men, as before; yet in the firſt ages of it, (impious enough otherwiſe) when the memory of the Creation, &amp; other great and miraculous works of God, was ſo freſh, and his preſence (by Angels and the like) ſo frequent among men; it could not poſsibly take place. The Devill then in thoſe dayes, when God did ſo manifeſtly intereſſe himſelf in the affaires of men, becauſe the time for Epicuriſme was not yet come, in ſtead of it, hee poyſoned men with an opinion, That <hi>God was of an envious nature:</hi> which was (as is ſhewed in the enſuing Treatiſe) the very ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument he uſed to our firſt father and mother, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> to make them tranſgreſs, and ſo to forfeit their firſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. And when ſome men by the very light of naturall humane reaſon that remained in them, began to diſcerne the impiety and abſurdity of this opinion, they fell into another, not altogether ſo impious, but more abſurd, that God is not omnipotent, and wanted not will, but power to amend what they conceived to be amiſs in the world: or, that there were two Authors and Creators of all things, the one good, and the other evill.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the firſt errors and extravagancies of men againſt the true doctrine of Gods <hi>Providence,</hi> and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the world, as it is taught by the holy Scriptures. Moſt men that have written of and for <hi>Providence,</hi> fall upon <hi>Epicurus</hi> and his opinions copiouſly enough; as indeed
<pb facs="tcp:113190:5"/>it is a large and copious argument, eſpecially ſince that by ſo many it hath been beaten and troden. But I know not of any that hath examined and refuted that more ancient error, or ſcarce taken notice of it: which nevertheleſſe is not leſſe, yea, in ſome reſpect I may ſay, more conſiderable. For as it is more ancient, ſo it may more clearely be derived from its firſt ſpring, miſtaken Scripture: which affords us a good argument for the antiquity and authenticknes of the Scriptures themſelves, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt atheiſts and infidels; as good, almoſt, as any can be. This is it therefore, that in this enſuing Treatiſe I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to my ſelfe, and endeavoured. I intend it (I confeſſe,) but as a part of a greater worke, concerning <hi>Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> in generall, which long agoe I have had in my thoughts. But whatever becomes of the reſt, this either as a part (if it ſhal pleaſe God to ſpare me life, and other opportunities ſhall ſerve) may begin; or if otherwiſe, ſtand by it ſelfe as a ſupplement to what hath already been written by others of that argument; and either way, give ſome ſatisfaction, I hope, in this maine point, to His glory, to whom whatſoever is not referred, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought much conſiderable.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. <hi>Lin.</hi> 33. Soon after. <hi>p</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 26. he did ſo. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 25. in his <abbr>XV.</abbr> Iliad. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l</hi> 6. <hi>heterogeneous. p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>Thou ſhalt know. p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113190:5"/>
            <head>THE ORIGINALL CAVSE OF TEMPORALL EVILS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the life of man in this world is full of troubles &amp; miſeries, is ſo common a complaint in the mouths of all men, of what ranke and quality ſoever they be; and ſo obvious a ſubject in Writers of all Ages, Nations and Profeſſions, as that it may well be reckoned among thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or known Principles, which common ſenſe teacheth, and Artiſts ground upon as indiſputable truths. Yet he that will ſee this common and beaten ſubject, moſt exquiſitely even in the judgement of humane reaſon, ſetting aſide the credit and authority of divine inſpiration, handled, needeth but goe to <hi>Eccleſiaſtes;</hi> the excellency of which diſcourſe he ſhall beſt underſtand, who judiciouſly compares it with the choiceſt, and moſt approved peeces, either old, or late, concerning that argument. The truth is, there hath been little ſaid by others upon that Theme, either for wit or wiſdome much conſiderable, which may not both be found here, and probably be ſuppoſed originally to have proceeded hence. I will give one inſtance. What among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, upon this ſubject of mans miſery, more famous, then that old ſaying, whereof they made one of their <hi>Sileni,</hi> (a degree above Philoſophers, among ancient Heathens) to be the authour, That it was the chiefeſt happineſſe, not to be born; next to that, quickly to die? Divers expreſſions of this ſaying by ſeverall Greek Poets (if any ſhal deſire to ſee them together, &amp; compare them) have been collected by <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> The matter is by <hi>Tully</hi> in his <hi>Tuſcul,</hi> briefly thus recorded: <hi>Fertur de Sileno fabella quaedam, &amp;c. There goes an old tale</hi> (or, <hi>ſtory:</hi> for ſo the word <hi>fabula</hi> ſometimes is taken) <hi>of a Silenus,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113190:6"/>who being taken by</hi> Midas <hi>the King, is ſaid to have given him a ranſome</hi> (or, <hi>reward) for his diſmiſſion: which was, that he taught him, how that it was a moſt happy thing not to be born; but in the next place, to die very ſoon.</hi> And this long before any memory of any either <hi>Midas</hi> or <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. ver. 1, 2, 3.</note> was thus delivered by wiſe <hi>Solomon: So I returned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered all the oppreſſions, that are done under the Sunne, and behold, &amp;c. Wherefore I praiſed the dead which are already dead, more then the living which are yet alive. Yea, better is he then both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not ſeen the evil work that is done under the Sun.</hi> Theſe words, <hi>Better is he then both they, &amp;c.</hi> miſunderſtood, might proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly occaſion that opinion of the ancienteſt Philoſophers, (of which we ſhall have occaſion for to ſay more afterwards) that the ſoules of men had a ſubſiſtence long before their incorporation, and were thus driven into this lower world, and confined into bodies, as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or Priſons, for ſome miſcariages in their former and better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <hi>Pliny</hi> the eldeſt, who had ſtudied the world as much as any man, and hath written of the world, (his Naturall Hiſtory I mean) more then any; who for his parts of nature, (wit, and curioſity) and other great advantages of fortune might be ſuppoſed to know as much as any other man; his obſervation is, that <hi>nullum frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius votum,</hi> no wiſh more frequent among men, then the wiſh of death; and thereupon his concluſion is, that <hi>Natura nihil brevitate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae praeſtitit melius:</hi> and elſewhere he cals death, <hi>pracipuum naturae bonum,</hi> the greateſt benefit of nature, or the greateſt bleſſing that heavens have vouchſafed unto mankind. Yet all this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if any judging of this life by what hath hitherto happened unto themſelves, and not much ſenſible of what they have known to happen unto others, be of another mind, and thinke better of the world then ſo; I might tell them of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> and others, who once thought themſelves the happieſt of men, and afterwards became notorious examples of mans miſery; I might alſo tell them, that among the miſeries of this life, thoſe that are publique, and extend unto many, (ſuch as are the miſeries of wars, ſlaughters, ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, plagues, famines, and the like; of which that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That both Sea and Land are full of miſeries,</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> hath generally beene true, and viſible at all times) are the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and thoſe which moſt affect a man, that is a man indeed; that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113190:6"/>is, truly ſociable, and communicable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Greek Philoſophers expreſſe it: this I ſay, and much more to this purpoſe I might tel them; but that, not the conſideration of our miſeries be they more or leſſe, or what opinion men have of them, is the ſubject by me here undertaken; but the originall cauſe of our miſeries, &amp; what was the opinion of ancienteſt Heathens about it; and how conſonant and agreeable it is with the truth of the holy Scriptures: ſuch conſonancy either of humane reaſon, (in times of Paganiſme) or ancient traditions with the Scriptures, having been accounted by ancient learned Chriſtians no ſmall evidence of the truth of the Scriptures themſelves, and by them therefore upon all occaſions with all poſſible care, and curioſity, ſifted, and inquired into. But before I come to what I have more directly propoſed to my ſelfe, I muſt be way of introduction take notice of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinions of theirs, that have much affinity with the former ſubject; and what relation they have to my main ſcope, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the progreſſe and concluſion of our diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>It is a common obſervation among the Ancients that there is no worldly good, which is not either tempered with ſome preſent evill; or at leaſt, hath the ſeeds in it ſelfe of ſome evill conſequence, and future inconvenience: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: or as ſome others, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>no worldly good, or pleaſure, is pure, and ſincere; unmixed, and untainted of the contrary.</hi> I know not any other ſubject that ancient both Hiſtorians and Philoſophers (Greeks eſpecially) more frequently inſiſt upon, if it come in their way; or more willingly digreſſe into. <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> in that excellent frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Metaphyſicks, handles it with admirable wit, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundity; ſhewing, that ſuch is the nature of this ſublunary world, as to conſiſt of contraries; and how one contrary doth beget ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: a curious ſpeculation; curiouſly handled and ſpeculated no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>Theophrastus</hi> onely, but by the authour of that polite Treatiſe <hi>De mundo,</hi> (too polite I doubt for <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> ſtile, though aſcribed unto him by divers ancients, beſides <hi>Apuleius,</hi> as <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Philoponus</hi>) the which <hi>Apuleius</hi> of old, and <hi>Budaeus</hi> of late have turned into Latin. One of the firſt, if not the very firſt now extant, in whom this obſervation of the mixture of ſweet and ſowre in worldly things, is to be found, is old <hi>Plato,</hi> who recordeth how his Maſter <hi>Socrates,</hi> that very day that he dranke his laſt and fatall cup, which made him immortall to all enſuing generations, having ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113190:7"/>rubbed his thigh or knee to allay the itch, which the fetters had occaſioned; and perceiving a kind of pleaſure to enſue upon it; took that occaſion to inſtruct his friends and auditors then preſent, concerning the nature of all worldly delights and pleaſures in theſe wo ds: <hi>How incongruous in my judgement, O friends, is that thing, which men uſually tearm ſweet? how marvellouſly</hi> (or, <hi>naturally</hi>) <hi>inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable it is to that, which becauſe they cannot be together at one time, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth contrary, pain? Yet nevertheleſſe, ſuch is their nature, that if a man purſue after the one and obtain it, it ſhall go very hard but he ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, as if both hanged by one string, to have part in the other alſo. And certainly had</hi> Aeſop <hi>thought of it, he would have made a Fable of it, how that God purpoſing to reconcile theſe two, ſweet and ſowre, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not being able; he did chain them together by the head</hi> (alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ex altero verticibus inter ſe contrariis deligavit, <hi>as</hi> Aulus Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius <hi>expreſſeth it;) ſo that whoſoever is partaker of the one, cannot be long without the other alſo; as now it hath happened unto me, the ſame fetter having cauſed firſt pain, and now pleaſure unto my thigh.</hi> So <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Plato.</hi> What <hi>Aeſop</hi> did not, learned and ingenious <hi>Camerarius</hi> hath ſince done; he hath contrived it into two fables, the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the text of <hi>Plato,</hi> the Reader ſhall find, if he pleaſe at the end of this Treatiſe. This was the practice of the Ancients, (I note it by the way, becauſe we have many examples of it in the holy Scriptures) by fables and parables, to worke upon men: and they found it a moſt powerfull and effectuall way; whereof <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Apollonius,</hi> hath a notable inſtance; &amp; it is in an argument of much affinity to this. But to return, it would be long even to name thoſe ſeverall ancient Authours, who have deſcanted upon it, and applied it to ſeverall occaſions. <hi>Pliny</hi> the latter among the Latins, in his incomparable Panegyrick, in few words, but as elegant and pithy, as they are ſhort, thus: <hi>Habet has vices conditio mortalium, ut adverſa ex ſecundis, ex adverſis ſecunda naſcantur, (naſcuntur,</hi> not <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcantur;</hi> as it is in ſome editions:) <hi>Occultas utrorumque ſemina De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; plerunque bonorum malorúmque cauſae ſub diversâ ſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> latent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which concerns us to take more eſpeciall notice of, is an other obſervation of the ſame Ancients, concerning all extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary worldly ſucceſſes, and more then uſuall proſperity in any kind, which they held generally to be very ominous, yea very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky; in ſo much as they were accounted wiſe and prudent, who could, if not altogether prevent, (which is not in the power of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113190:7"/>man) yet by certain art and cunning, temper and allay ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of fortune. Whether this was intended by <hi>Menander,</hi> or no, (that famous Comick) I know not; for he might have another aim: but his words are pertinent:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of all unhappineſſe among men, the chief cauſe is, Much</hi> (or, <hi>too much) happineſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The opinion may ſeeme ſtrange, but the practice of many of them, upon it, much more; and the grounds both of the one and of the other, when well weighed and conſidered, moſt of all. <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> ſhall be the firſt from whom we will take our information a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, as being the firſt of ancient Hiſtorians, now extant; and in that reſpect, for his antiquity, to us moſt conſiderable. He tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth upon it often, upon divers occaſions; but moſt fully and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively (though not as from himſelfe there, but in the perſon of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſis,</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> a Prince of great renown, among the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents) in his third book, and fortieth chapter, as it is uſually divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>Polycrates,</hi> King, or rather Tyrant of <hi>Samos;</hi> (an Iſland of the <hi>Egean</hi> ſea, bordering upon <hi>Aſia,</hi> once ſo flouriſhing, that even the hens of it were proverbially ſaid to be milked; but now in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner altogether forſaken of inhabitants) having had for a long time more then ordinary ſucceſſe in all his enterpriſes, his felicity all that while not croſſed in any other kinde either at home or abroad; <hi>Amaſis</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> his great friend and confederate, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to have writen a Letter to him about it; the copy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of according to <hi>Herodotus</hi> was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amaſis</hi> to <hi>Polycrates,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, haec mandat. <hi>as</hi> Camerarius <hi>renders it</hi>) <hi>ſaith thus: That thou doſt well and prosper, is no ſmall joy unto me, as thy friend and confederate; but I must tell thee plainly, that theſe great and overflowing ſucceſſes doe not pleaſe me, who know ful wel, the nature of the Deity, how envious it is. It is my wiſh concerning my own ſelf, and the ſame I wiſh to all that are deare unto me, ſometimes to proſper, and ſometimes to miſcarry; and in this viciſſitude of fortunes to paſſe my life; rather then without any alteration to proſper. For I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet could heare of any, who having thus proſpered long, did not, at the last, end in an univerſall deſtruction. Be thou therefore perſwaded by me, and take this courſe with thy proſperity: Conſider ſeriouſly with thy ſelfe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113190:8"/>what thing thou hast thou moſt esteemeſt, and for the loſſe of which then wouldeſt be moſt grieved: this, whatever it be, caſt away, that it may never be ſeen again: And for the time to come likewiſe, if thy ſucceſſes ſhall not interchangeably be varied, help thy ſelfe in the ſame manner that I have now ſhewed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Amaſis</hi> to his friend <hi>Polycrates:</hi> And <hi>Polycrates</hi> being before, as is probable, poſſeſſed with the ſame principles of the nature of the Deity, as <hi>Amaſis</hi> was, was eaſily perſwaded. He threw a ring, which of all his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or precious jewels, he moſt valued, into the Sea, never likely, as a man would have thought, to ſee it more; but his good luck, or ill luck rather, as they apprehended it, was ſuch, that he could not find occaſion of griefe, though he ſought it; not when he ſought it, at leaſt. For his ring was ſoon after brought to him againe. How this happened, and other particulars of the ſtory, but eſpecially the lamentable <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of his life, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his friend <hi>Amaſis</hi> his praediction, may be read in <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dotus</hi> at large: and more briefly in others, (as <hi>Strabo</hi> for one by name) that had it from him. This narration to ſome that know nothing but their own times may ſeem ridiculous. I cannot peremptorily undertake for the truth of it: but for the probability, (that one particular of the miraculous return of his ring excepted) I can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both from the opinion and practice of divers others in aftera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Some write of <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> a famous <hi>Theban;</hi> ſome of <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon;</hi> that after high and unexpected victories, they became (in their outward cariage and deportment, at leaſt) very ſorrowfull, more like mourners, then triumphers, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, then through feare of ſome great eminent diſaſter, which they by this provident ſenſibleneſſe, and voluntary humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation hoped they ſhould prevent: Of this latter, <hi>Niceph. Gregoras;</hi> of the former, <hi>Iſid. Peluſiota,</hi> (not to mention others) bear record, and commend them for it: Chriſtians both, the one an Hiſtorian of later Greece; the other <hi>(Iſidorus)</hi> an ancient Father, one of S. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> Diſciples. <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that great Monarch, (in whoſe daies the Saviour of the world was born, and took upon him <hi>the form of a ſervant) ſtipem quotannis, die certe, emendicabat à popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suetonius</hi> of him) <hi>cavam manum aſſes porrigentibus prabens:</hi> that is, in plain Engliſh, that once in the year he was wont to turn begger, and (<hi>cavâ manu,</hi> that is, in the moſt ignominious way of taking) received almes of ſuch of the common people, as would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113190:8"/>give him. <hi>Suetonius</hi> ſaith no more of it then ſo, neither in thoſe days needed he, to be underſtood; but learned men, and well ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in antiquity, that have writen upon him, ſhew the reaſon. He miſtruſted his own long continued felicity, (though varied by many croſſe chances and accidents, whereof <hi>Pliny</hi> the elder hath made a whole Chapter in his Hiſtory of the world) and dreaded (upon the ſame ſuppoſition as <hi>Amaſis</hi> in <hi>Herodotus</hi>) that ſo dreadfull, in thoſe days, <hi>invidiam Numinis.</hi> So <hi>Camillus</hi> a Romane Captaine, having with marvellous ſucceſſe delivered his Country from miſerable thraldome, he made it, ſay ancient Hiſtorians, his requeſt unto God, that if ſuch hap and ſucceſſe was too great to eſcape the ſtroaks of Heavens envy, himſelf, and not the Publique might be the object of thoſe ſtroaks: which they ſay befel to him according to his deſire; firſt, a ſuddain light fall; and afterwards, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from thoſe whom he had delivered.</p>
            <p>To theſe I ſhall adde but one paſſage of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in his <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> that it may be compared with <hi>Herodotus,</hi> becauſe the one will not a little give both light and credit unto the other. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus,</hi> according to the ſupputation of moſt accurate Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Hiſtorians, publiquely (as the manner was in thoſe days) recited his Hiſtories about the year ſince the Creation, 3504. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> all know, lived under <hi>Trajan;</hi> ſo that the diſtance of time between <hi>Herodotus,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch,</hi> is of about 600. years. <hi>Plutarch</hi> then having related the particulars of this <hi>Paul. Aemil.</hi> his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, (according to the Roman faſhion) for his wonderfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe againſt <hi>Perſeus,</hi> a Potent King, (the laſt of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and the laſt of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great his ſucceſſors,) having in a very little time got both King and Kingdome into his own hands; and now paſſing to the narration of thoſe ſad accidents, that befell him about the ſame time; to wit, the ſuddain death of two of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he kept at home, as deareſt unto him, the one wherof died five days before; and the other four days after this publick triumphing:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all this,</hi> Aemilius (ſaith he) <hi>was admired by all men, envied by none that were good and vertuous: but that there is a certain Deity, whoſe proper task it is to bring down lower</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as it were by pumping</hi>) <hi>all great and overſwelling proſperities, and ſo to mixe and temper every man's life, that no man may be happy in this world, without a rub, or a ſtain: So that according to</hi> Homer, <hi>thoſe are to be accounted moſt happy indeed, &amp; to fare beſt, whoſe fortunes are varied with a viciſſitude of events in both kindes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113190:9"/>
            <p>The place of <hi>Homer</hi> to which he refers, are thoſe noted verſes in the laſt of his Iliads, (elſewhere cited by <hi>Plutarch</hi> at large) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the Poet fains <hi>Jupiter</hi> to have two barrels or veſſels by him, the one of good, the other of evill luck; out of which he diſtributes unto every man his ſeverall fortune. Thoſe men, ſaith he, to whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> deales out of both veſſels, they are happy: but thoſe unto whom he deals out of one onely, they are moſt unfortunate. It is not ſo expreſly ſaid by <hi>Homer,</hi> that they are unhappy unto whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> deals out of either veſſell without mixture; but he is ſo interpreted by <hi>Plato,</hi> (whoſe words are not ſo clearly rendred by the Latin Interpreters, as they might have been) in his Books, <hi>De Republica,</hi> the 11. Book: which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is here followed by <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe few examples may ſerve to ſhew both their practice and their opinion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſuch is the nature of the Deity (of ſome Deity at leaſt) to envy men. It was a thing ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in their mouths upon all occaſions, that hardly ſhall you read any ancient Authour, either Greek or Latin, where you finde it not, or ſome traces of it. We ſhall meet with divers paſſages as we go on, which I forbear here, to avoid repetition. There be ſome ancient Authors who ſeem to derive it from <hi>Herodotus,</hi> as the firſt of that opinion; others, from <hi>Simonides,</hi> a Poet of very great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity: we ſhall produce their words, and ſhew the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have done. A ſtrange thing it is to obſerve how apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſome were (none of the meaneſt neither, but men learned, and reputed wiſe and ſober, in common eſtimation of men) in this kinde: ſo apprehenſive, that they durſt not acknowledge their own, though but ordinary welfare, without an excuſe, left they might ſeem to boaſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lin. Epiſt. lib.</hi> v. <hi>Ep.</hi> 6.</note> and ſo provoke envy. We may obſerve it in <hi>Pliny,</hi> the latter, plainly: In a place, commending the wholeſome ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of his Country houſes, <hi>Mei quoque</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nuſquam ſalubriùs degunt, uſque adhuc certè neminem ex its quos eduxeram me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, venia ſit dicto, ibi amiſi.</hi> So in the VIII. Book, and the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Epiſtle, having ſpoken of his wives miſcarying of a child, and her great danger upon it, <hi>Fuit alioquin,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in ſummo diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; impunè dixiſſe liceat, fuit.</hi> He durſt not acknowledge her to be paſt danger (to which purpoſe the word <hi>fuit,</hi> is very emphaticall) without ſome ſuch qualification, to deprecate envy, <hi>impunè dixiſſe liceat;</hi> as before, <hi>venia ſit dicto:</hi> being both to one effect. Many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113190:9"/>ſuch paſſages occurre in ancient Authours, where Interpreters and Commentators not aware of this ſo generally received opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are much put to it; as it ſeems <hi>Dio Caſſius</hi> was, though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leſſe then two ages after, about that fact of <hi>Augustus</hi> his yearly begging, which out of <hi>Suetonius</hi> we have ſpoken of. But beſides this, that which ſometimes breeds no ſmall obſcurity, is the variety of tearms uſed by Authours in this argument: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the like: we ſhall ſay ſomewhat of the chiefeſt of them at the end of this Treatiſe; that we be not too long upon words, before we come to the matter it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now when they thus complained of the <hi>envy,</hi> or <hi>malignity</hi> of ſuperiour powers, that ſome of them underſtood ſuch powers, as they worſhipped for gods, is not to be doubted, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which is all one) that is, <hi>God,</hi> or, <hi>the Deity,</hi> being the word often uſed in this argument; not by <hi>Herodotus</hi> onely, but divers other Greek Authors; as <hi>Deus</hi> is, by Latin Authors, not a few. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>daemon,</hi> or, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the more uſuall word upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this occaſion; whether God, or the Devill, or ſomewhat equivalent to what we call the Devill, was by them that uſed the word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, is a queſtion not very eaſie to be reſolved, if well ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and throughly canvaſſed. Ancient Grammarians and ſome others obſerve of it, that by <hi>Homer</hi> and other Ancients it is promiſcuouſly uſed for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>God:</hi> which I thinke no man will make a queſtion of, that hath ever but looked into any of them. The ſame Grammarians, or ſome of them, doe alſo obſerve, that the word is otherwiſe uſed by <hi>Heſiod,</hi> for an inferiour kind, once men, and afterwards immortalized, and deified to a certain degree of Deity, different from the firſt kinde; which will not concern us: but, whether of old, originally; or, if not originally, when then the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> began to be uſed in that worſt ſenſe we now ſpake of, either by ſome, ſometimes; or commonly and generally by moſt; is a queſtion both among ancient and later Writers; and it will concern us much to know the truth of it; if by any means it can be known. I ſhall therefore endeavour to ſay what may be ſaid of it upon good and ſatisfactory grounds.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then it muſt be granted that ſoone after Chriſt the word <hi>daemon</hi> in queſtion, began generally, not among Chriſtians only, but even Heathens, in common uſe to be taken in the worſt ſenſe. This we learn from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> whoſe words in his Apologetick,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113190:10"/>are:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul. Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. ca.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Sciunt daemonas Philoſophi, &amp;c. Etiam vulgus indoctum in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum maledicti frequentat. Nam &amp; Satanam principem hujus mali ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris proinde de propriâ conſcientiâ anima eadem ex ſacramenti voce pronuntiat.</hi> So I find the words ſet forth in the laſt <hi>Paris</hi> edition of the yeare 1635. which pretendeth to follow <hi>Rigaltius</hi> his Text, <hi>per omnia,</hi> but doth not here, I am ſure. The common expoſition of the words, grounded upon that falſe reading, is much contrary to <hi>Tertullian</hi> his aim and intention; which was to tell us, not what Chriſtians thought, or were taught in their Sacraments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>daemons:</hi> but what even Heathens themſelves that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped them did in their ordinary language, unwittingly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wils, as it were, acknowledge of them: as is more fully declared by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> long after <hi>Tertullian;</hi> whoſe words will give much light to thoſe of <hi>Tertullians.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> then in his <hi>De Civit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in De Civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Det l.</hi> IX <hi>ca.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Dei,</hi> having firſt ſpoken of the acception, or uſe of the word in holy Scriptures, and among Chriſtians, goes on in theſe words: <hi>Et hanc loquendi conſuetudinem in tantum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli uſquequaque ſecuti ſunt, ut eorum etiam qui Pagani appellantur, &amp; Deos multos ac daemones colendos eſſe contendunt, nullus ferè ſit tam literatus &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctus,</hi> (<hi>Tertullian</hi> goes no further then <hi>vulgus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctum:</hi> but now as Chriſtianiſme prevailed, the word grew more infamous every day) <hi>qui audeat in laude vel ſervo ſuo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, Daemonium habes: ſed quilibet hoc dicere voluerit, non ſe aliter accipi quam maledicere voluiſſe non dubitare non poſſit.</hi> So elſewhere, why <hi>Apuleius</hi> did entitle his booke <hi>De Deo Socratis,</hi> and not <hi>De Daemonio</hi> rather, whereas in that very book he diſputes at large, and maintains it to have been a <hi>Daemon,</hi> (not a <hi>Devill,</hi> but one of thoſe ſubordinate powers to the Deity, in <hi>Heſiod</hi>'s acception) and not a God; the ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Ita enim per ſanam doctrinam</hi> &amp;c. becauſe through the Goſpel of Chriſt the word <hi>daemon</hi> was become ſo generally odious, and abominable, that whoever had read the title, <hi>De daemone Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> before he had read the book it ſelfe, wherein the <hi>daemon</hi> is commended as one of the better kind, would have thought <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> by that title, to have been poſſeſſed and out of his wits. <hi>Hierocles</hi> alſo, a Heathen Philoſopher upon <hi>Pythagoras</hi> (ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called) his <hi>Golden verſes,</hi> acknowledges almoſt as much, in effect: but ſo obſcurely, that without S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> help I ſhould hardly have underſtood him. This <hi>Hierocles</hi> when he lived, I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113190:10"/>know not certainly; this we are ſure enough of, that he lived ſince Chriſt a good while, and before S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in thoſe verſes, which in former times would have paſſed currant enough for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (often occurring in ancient Inſcriptions, in Latin <hi>Dii Stygii</hi> called) he expounds of men emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in knowledge and vertue, taking <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, contrary to the common uſe of that word. For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of it ſelf ſounding then but ill in the ears of moſt men; he knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in its ordinary acception, (for <hi>ſubterraneos,</hi> or <hi>infernales</hi>) were put to it, it would be a hard thing to perſwade men to take it in the better ſenſe, for any other then meer Devils, Therefore not content with this bare interpretation, he adds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for further prevention, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>For God forbid,</hi> that is, <hi>any ſhould conceive that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of theſe verſes would bid us worſhip any evill kinde,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he means, or, <hi>evill spirits</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>as ſome perchance might ſurmiſe according to the more vulgar uſe of that word.</hi> Had learned <hi>Salmaſius</hi> thought well of this, and better conſidered of the text of <hi>Hierocles,</hi> he would have been, I beleeve, of another opinion concerning the right meaning of theſe words, then that he is of in his Preface to the Arabick Tranſlation of <hi>Cebes</hi> his Table.</p>
            <p>Now to return to <hi>Tertullians</hi> words, (which I muſt deſire the Reader once more to look upon) it hath been obſerved by ſome, that <hi>exſecramenti,</hi> in one word, and not <hi>exſacramenti,</hi> is the reading of ſome ancient Manuſcripts; and <hi>exſecramentum,</hi> or rather, <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum,</hi> in <hi>Tertullian</hi> his African Latin, for <hi>execratio,</hi> or <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio,</hi> is by ſome others well expounded alſo; who, ſo far, ſaw the right meaning of the words, but did not, or could not ſufficiently prove it; which now I think no man will make any queſtion of. But whereas <hi>Tertullian</hi> both here and elſewhere, in his book <hi>De Teſtimonio Animae,</hi> doth ſeem to affirm (which hath moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Expoſitors, and made them to underſtand him of Chriſtians) that not only the word <hi>Daemon</hi> but that of <hi>Satan</hi> alſo, was even by Heathens frequently uſed in <hi>detestation,</hi> or by way of curſing; whereof I know no <hi>veſtigium</hi> in any other Author extant, but much againſt it extant in divers; I therefore conceive that the word <hi>pronuntiant</hi> (which is the word in both places) muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not of words expreſſed or uttered; but of a ſenſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113190:11"/>ſentence (and ſo the word <hi>pronuntio,</hi> is very proper) that may be inferred, as implicitly contained in the common uſe of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word <hi>daemon,</hi> which was ſpoken of: as if he ſaid, That whileſt they commonly uſed the word <hi>daemon</hi> in deteſtation, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their averſneſſe from a thing; they did at the ſame time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly ſubſcribe to the truth of the Scriptures, which ſet out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us <hi>Satan,</hi> the Prince of <hi>daemons,</hi> as the authour of all evill. The very word <hi>proinde</hi> in the Text of <hi>Tertullian</hi> (by which his <hi>denique</hi> in that other paſſage muſt be expounded) doth imply ſome ſuch thing, that it is but by way of collection or inference that <hi>Satan</hi> is thus pronounced againſt. <hi>Nam &amp; Satanam principem hujus mali generis proinde de propria conſcientia anima, eâdem exſecramenti voce pronuntiat;</hi> as it was well before in ſome former editions. And <hi>Rigaltius</hi> his edition varies but very little from this. In ſtead of <hi>anima,</hi> it hath <hi>animae,</hi> which comes all to one: but that he that reades <hi>Tertullian</hi> in <hi>De Teſtimon. Animae,</hi> cap. 2. will, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, judge that the righter. But now for the ſenſe of the words, he that ſhall reade that learned man his Obſervations upon this and that other paſſage of <hi>Tertul. De Teſtimon. Animae.</hi> (cap. 3.) will I hope (if he mark well <hi>Tertul.</hi> his words) think the better of what hath here been ſaid of them.</p>
            <p>We take it then for granted, that the word <hi>daemon,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſoon after Chriſt, began to be taken in the worſt ſenſe; of the time before is all the queſtion, not yet reſolved. There be, who becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is taken ſometimes in the worſt, and ſometimes in the better ſenſe; for a happy, ſometimes; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a wretched unfortunate man; infer upon it that therfore the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe was originally <hi>vox media,</hi> as they call them, as properly ſignifying an evill, as a good ſpirit. But why not rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo taken and uſed on both ſides, upon a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that all mans happineſſe, or unhappineſſe, (as by divers Heathens is maintained) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, (according to ſome) from God immediately; according to others, (taking the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>fortune;</hi> as frequently) from fortune; and that the endevours of men in that kinde can but little, or nothing. Whence <hi>Eustathius</hi> upon a place of <hi>Homer, The words,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>may alſo be underſtood of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>who is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So <hi>Orpheus,</hi> (though not that ancient <hi>Orpheus,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mentioned by <hi>Plato,</hi> and by ancient Fathers; yet an ancient
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113190:11"/>Poet, yea <hi>perantiquus,</hi> as ſome very learned and judicious ſpeak of him) in his hymn or prayer intituled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he makes the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the authour, as of happineſſe, to ſome; ſo of miſery, to others. There is as much ambiguity in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is uſually taken in the worſt ſenſe for <hi>daemone corript, vel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitari,</hi> to be poſſeſſed: but by heathen Authors for the moſt part, in the better ſenſe, for <hi>numine afflari,</hi> to be inſpired: and ſo it ſhould be tranſlated indeed, in divers places, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Chriſtian Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters impoſe, unwittingly I beleeve, their own ſenſe upon hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen Authors, wrongfully. Again, whereas ancient Heathens, Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and others ſpeak often of hurts, and miſchiefes done or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by <hi>daemons,</hi> it is no good argument to inferre thereupon that therefore the word <hi>daemon</hi> of it ſelfe, is ſometimes taken in the worſt ſenſe, it being as ordinary with them to aſcribe ſuch things to their beſt gods, as is at large proved by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and ſome others; and that in thoſe very places ſometimes, where they tel us of either their evil <hi>daemons,</hi> or evils done by their <hi>daemons,</hi> they forbear not the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but uſe it promiſcuouſly, calling the ſame ſometimes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſometimes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as I could ſhew by divers inſtances: ſo that we can inferre no more, upon this, of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then may be inferred of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo. The word <hi>Angel,</hi> is a good word of it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, alwayes taken in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſenſe when abſolutely uſed; yet <hi>Pſalme</hi> 78. <hi>ver.</hi> 49. we are told of <hi>evill angels. He caſt upon them the fierceneſſe of his anger, wrath, &amp; indignation and trouble, by ſending evil angels among them.</hi> Some Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors by theſe <hi>evill angels</hi> underſtand devils, or evill ſpirits: but others with no leſſe probability, good angels. Good angels may be the inſtruments and miniſters of temporall evill, and in that reſpect called <hi>evill Angels.</hi> But as for this place, I for my part rather incline to them, <hi>Rabbins</hi> and others, who by <hi>evill angels</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>evils,</hi> or plagues themſelves, which were ſent upon <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and this the rather, becauſe I find that kind of expreſſion to have been familiar to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> of old. So for example, where <hi>Pſalme</hi> 89.49. according to the Hebrew it is, <hi>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death;</hi> the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe renders it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee the angel of death?</hi> And <hi>Hab.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 5. according to the Hebrew: <hi>Before him went the Peſtilence:</hi> the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>from before him was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113190:12"/>ſent the angel of death;</hi> and ſo elſewhere. Theſe kind of expreſſions, whether uſed the better to teach us, that all things life, death; good, evill, that happen to men in this world, are from God originally, whoſe miniſters theſe Angels (called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſpirits,</hi> in the New Teſt.) are; or by a kind of figure, called by the Grecians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereby things inſenſible, incorporeall, are made to live; vertues and vices (which ſome <hi>Stoicks</hi> really beleeved) repreſented as <hi>animals,</hi> and the like; I ſhall not here inquire fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther. But it ſeaſonably puts me in mind of an interpretation of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> much to this purpoſe, which I remember to have read in <hi>Dio Chryſoſtomus,</hi> in a long Oration of <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Cynick, to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great. It is a very conſiderable interpretation, but not to our purpoſe here: and therefore it ſhall ſerve to have mentioned it.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have found nothing, that could induce us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was of old (as is affirmed by ſome) and before Chriſt <hi>vox media,</hi> &amp; taken ſometimes even by Heathens in the worſt ſenſe: much leſſe, that it originally ſignified a Devill, or an evill ſpirit, as is by others affirmed. If <hi>Plutarch</hi> help us not, I doubt no man will: out of whom I finde two paſſages quoted to this purpoſe. The firſt is, out of his <hi>De I ſide &amp; O ſiride,</hi> (to which they might have added another paſſage of the ſame author in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where he hath the ſame words againe) where ſpeaking of the opinion of many, (which it ſeems was <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchs</hi> opinion too, as appears, not by this only, but by other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes and paſlages of his) concerning two contrary <hi>principia,</hi> or <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;</hi> the one <hi>good,</hi> and the other <hi>evill:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. &amp;c. that is, <hi>Of theſe two, the better they call,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>god: the other, they call,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>daemon: as Zoroaſter the Magus,</hi> &amp;c. Here firſt it muſt be obſerved, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are <hi>Plutarch's</hi> own words, or interpretation: for the words uſed by them he ſpeaks of, <hi>Zoroaster</hi> and others, were, (as himſelf ſoon often tels us) <hi>Oromazis, (Oromaides</hi> rather, as it is in that other paſſage we told you but now of) and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manius.</hi> Secondly, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> long before <hi>Plutarch</hi> writing of the ſame thing, expreſſeth it otherwiſe, and it is not unlikely that <hi>Plutarch,</hi> though he kept not preciſely to his Authors words, might take it, if not out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> yet of ſome other (for divers are named by <hi>Dio. Laertius</hi> that write the ſame) that related it as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113190:12"/>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth. Now, <hi>Ariſtotle in his firſt De Philoſophiâ</hi> (they are <hi>Diog. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertius</hi> his words in his <hi>Proem</hi> to the Philoſophers lives) <hi>writeth that the Magi were ancienter then the Aegyptians; and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them, there be two principles,</hi> (or <hi>authors) the one a good, and the other an evill daemon;</hi> (or, <hi>God) and that the firſt, is called</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (or, <hi>Jupiter) and</hi> Oromaſdes; <hi>and the ſecond,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (or, <hi>Hell) and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimanius: <hi>which</hi> Hermippus, Eudoxus, <hi>and</hi> Theopompus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From which words, it is evident, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> language is all one: and that all we can inſerre from <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s words, is but this, (which is no more in effect then hath already been granted and proved) that in his dayes, who was ſome 100. years after Chriſt, and ſome 40. or 50. before <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> began in ordinary language to be taken in the worſt part, &amp; ſometimes in the writings of learned men alſo.</p>
            <p>The ſecond paſſage out of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> is out of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <hi>Table-talk of the ſeven wiſe men</hi> at a ſolemn Feaſt, where to a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion propoſed by <hi>Amaſis</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>What is moſt profitable,</hi> or <hi>beneficiall?</hi> anſwer is made, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God:</hi> againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>What moſt pernicious in the world?</hi> it is anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>a daemon,</hi> or <hi>the daemon.</hi> But what is the cenſure even there upon this anſwer? that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that it is a bold, inſolent, unheard of anſwer and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as the word is uſed oftentimes upon ſuch occaſions: or if you take the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as ordinarily; <hi>that it is a bold Anſwer, &amp; of dangerous conſequence:</hi> of dangerous conſequence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as making Devils of thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they beleeved, &amp; worſhipped as Gods: an anſwer then, not grounded upon any publickly known and approved difference, or different ſenſe of the words, but upon the conceit of one ſingle man. That this is the ſenſe of the words may further appear by another paſſage of the ſame <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in his tractat <hi>De defectu Oracul,</hi> where at the mention of <hi>evill daemons,</hi> one of the interlocutors is much ſcandalized, as at a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and abſurd. And yet the queſtion there was not whether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of it ſelfe, or abſolutely, was ever taken in the worſt ſenſe, (which is our queſtion here) and muſt needs have offended much more; but whether there were any ſuch indeed as evill ſpirits, or daemons. Beſides what may be ſuſpected not without ſome ground, that here alſo <hi>Plutarch</hi> might alter, not of purpoſe, but heedleſly, the ancient words, and fit them to the dialect of his times. And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113190:13"/>this I muſt alſo anſwer if another place of the ſame <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſhould be objected, where ſpeaking of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt principles of all things, he writeth that he the ſaid <hi>Pythagoras</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, <hi>the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, God; and the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>(duitie) daemon.</hi> And indeed it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that ſpeaking of the ſame thing in divers other places, I doe not find that any where elſe, but in this, he tels us of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; no not in his Treatiſe <hi>De Iſide &amp; Oſir.</hi> where nevertheleſſe we find divers other names and appellations collected, whereby the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> extolled their ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and as much vilified and reviled the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Having therefore taken ſome pains to ſatisfie my ſelfe, as not willing to paſſe by ſo notable an advantage to my cauſe, if I might have ſound grounds to convince me; I muſt now deſire to be excuſed, and that I may not be thought to prevaricate, if I dare not ground either upon S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his bare aſſertion, who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where doth peremptorily determine that <hi>daemon</hi> was at the firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the worſt ſenſe for a <hi>Devil:</hi> or, <hi>evill ſpirit;</hi> and doth acutely diviſe the reaſon both of the different, with ſome; and promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe of the word, with others: not upon him I ſay; nor upon <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his <hi>Admon. ad G.</hi> (not to name others) his obſervation, who becauſe <hi>Homer</hi> cals ſome of their chiefeſt Deities (among Heathens) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (even among the Heathens of his time) were taken ordinarily for evill ſpirits, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing about Tombes and Sepulchres, &amp;c.</hi> therefore he conceits that of purpoſe he did did ſo call them (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to diſhonour and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie them. In the Edition of <hi>Clemens</hi> it is printed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and tranſlated, (then which nothing could be more contrary to his meaning) <hi>qui illos improbè honoravit:</hi> whereas it muſt of neceſſity be read, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being here for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, of purpoſe, and not caſually, or unwittingly) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Though the very context well weighed, and other conſiderations will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force this correction; yet to prevent all cavill and oppoſition, I ſhall make <hi>Clemens</hi> to be his own Expoſitor, whoſe words in this very book, ſome 8. or 9. pages after are theſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>And not</hi> Menander <hi>only, but</hi> Homer <hi>alſo and</hi> Euripides, <hi>and divers other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets freely reprove your Gods, and make no ſcruple at all as freely to revile
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113190:13"/>them.</hi> Other ſuch conceits of <hi>Homer,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi>'s oblique reproofs of the ſuperſtition of their times, other Fathers, beſides <hi>Clemens,</hi> have, which compared with this might adde further light unto it, if it needed it; which it doth not. To return therefore to our word, and to conclude ſomewhat; Upon all that hath been ſaid hitherto about it, I conceive that from books now extant and remaining, (<hi>Clemens</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> perchance might ſee many in their dayes that are not now to be ſeen) it cannot perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily be affirmed, or made good, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>daemon</hi> uſed by the Latins, before Chriſt and Chriſtianity, was taken in the worſt ſenſe, being put abſolutely and ſimply, as Crammarians ſpeak; that is, without any addition, or limitation; but either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently taken for the very ſame as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which is the more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary uſe:) or if for an inferiour and ſubordinate kind, even then, for good, and not evil ſpirits. Which uſe of the word after Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo remained among the learned Heathens, as may appear by their writings, very common, even then, though not altogether ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as before; but among the vulgar, it ſoon began to alter, and in time, quite loſt its firſt uſe. However, nothing that hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been ſaid doth hinder, but that the word many years, yea, and ages perchance before <hi>Homer</hi> might be taken otherwiſe then in his time and afterwards, and originally ſignifie a <hi>devill,</hi> or <hi>evill ſpirit,</hi> there being in all languages examples of divers words, which in proceſſe of time have loſt their primitive uſe and ſignification, and uſurped another, farre different, yea ſometimes contrary. This may be ſuppoſed, but ſuppoſed onely. And here the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ymology of the word, if certainly known and agreed upon, might happily ſtand us in ſome ſtead: but neither are ancient Greek Grammarians and others that ſpeak of it, altogether of one opinion about it; and among the learned of theſe later times, ſince the knowledge of tongues hath flouriſhed more then ever, it is not agreed whether it be originally a Greek word or no, ſome fetching it from the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, and ſome from the Arabick; ſo that in ſuch variety of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diſſonancy of judgements I ſhall not take upon me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily to determine, ſo as to build upon it: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe what I thinke of the right Etymology of the word, and upon what grounds, (which will require more words then I can think ſeaſonable in this place) ſhall have a place by it ſelfe at the end of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113190:14"/>
            <p>In the mean time, what need we ſo much to ſtand upon words, if the thing it ſelfe can be proved? to wit, that there was an old tradition among ancient Heathens of certain (however called) evill ſpirits, who envied mankind, and out of meer envy and malignity did what they could to miſchiefe and annoy them. Somewhat to this purpoſe we ſhall have occaſion to ſay when we ſhall treat of the Etymology of the word, what opinion the Ancients had concerning thoſe they called <hi>heroes.</hi> But without it or any thing elſe, one ſingle, but very pregnant and pertinent te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Plutarch</hi> may ſerve to doe the deed. I ſhall therefore firſt ſet down his words, for their ſakes that are not ſo well verſed in the Greek tongue, in Engliſh; and then in Greek: rather here, then at the end of this Treatiſe, with ſome others, becauſe they are words of ſo much conſequence to us: and not onely ſet them down in Greek, but alſo with ſome Notes and illuſtrations make them plainer, and clearer, and more unqueſtionable, then otherwiſe they would be to every Reader. <hi>Plutarch</hi> then in the beginning of his <hi>Dio,</hi> having ſpoken of ſome apparitions of ſpirits, &amp; taken notice of ſome mens opinion, that deny all ſuch apparitions to be really what they are pretended, but meerly to proceed from conceit and phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, incidentall to children, and women, and ſuch onely who through ſickneſſe, or any other diſtemper of the body, are not well in their wits; <hi>But on the other ſide,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if ſuch as</hi> Brutus <hi>and</hi> Dio, <hi>grave men and learned in Philoſophy, not apt eaſily to be be moved, or to be wrought upon by any paſſions, were nevertheleſſe ſo affected with theſe apparitions, that they did acknowledge it unto others; we ſhall, I doubt, be enforced to allow of that very ancient opinion (though it may ſeem to ſome no leſſe ridiculous then it is ancient) that there are certain wicked and envious daemons,</hi> (or, <hi>ſpirits), who envy good men, and oppoſe their actions, by ſudden fears and troubleſome phancies, endevouring to ſupplant them in their vertuous courſes: and this of purpoſe, leſt if they ſhould continue unſhaken and untainted unto the end in the purſuit of that which is right and juſt, they ſhould after their lives attain to more happineſſe then themſelves have obtained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Plutarch</hi> in my Engliſh; his own words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113190:14"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Thoſe that have paſſions,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſomewhere in his <hi>Politicks) cannot judg of the truth.</hi> where by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as here alſo in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> we muſt not onely underſtand thoſe ſtronger affections, as anger, love, hatred, joy, ſorrow, and the like; but all diſordinate appetites, all vicious exorbitances from right reaſon, as vain-glory, covetouſnes, pride, ſelf-conceit, and the like; all which come under the notion of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or paſſions, and have been noted by beſt writers, not Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers onely, but Hiſtorians and others, ſome more violently, ſome more inſenſibly, but as dangerouſly, to corrupt reaſon, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſway the judgement, even of the moſt rationall otherwiſe, and quick-ſighted.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may be alſo tranſlated, <hi>abſurd, incredible,</hi> or <hi>ſtrange:</hi> and this may be referred partly to their opinion, who laugh (as he told us before, and whereof you may reade more in <hi>Lucian's Dialogue</hi> inſcribed <hi>Philopſeudes,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) at all apparitions, as meer fables and fopperies: and partly to what here follows, of the envy, wickedneſſe and oppoſition of ſome daemons. As for apparitions, it is a large ſubject, and of great conſequence. I purpoſe to treat of it hereafter by it ſelfe, God willing, and ſhall endaevour to ſatisfie all that are not yet ſatisfied, as about Apparitions, ſo about Witches. In the meane time I ſhall referre them to what learned M. <hi>Voſſius</hi> (my worthy friend) hath written in his elaborate Commentations <hi>De Origine Idololatriae,</hi> lib <abbr>I.</abbr> c. <abbr>VI.</abbr> But it is more probable that this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here muſt be referred to that which follows of wicked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, or daemons. For eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſince Chriſt, &amp; Chriſtianity far ſpread in the world, there were eminent Philoſophers, that thought it much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with reaſon, to beleeve any ſuch. Will you have ſome of their reaſons? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is not eaſie to make theſe words runne as ſmoothly in the Engliſh as they doe in the Originall; but the ſenſe is this: <hi>If any beleeve that there are any evill daemons,</hi> (or, <hi>that the daemons are evill) I aske, if they have their power from the Gods, how then evill? If not from them, then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113190:15"/>are not the Gods authors of all things. If not authors, then either becauſe they would, but cannot; or becauſe they can, but will not, neither of which is agreeable to the nature of God.</hi> They are the words of <hi>Salluſtius</hi> the Philoſopher in his <hi>De Diis &amp; Mundo,</hi> the XII. Chapter. Much to this purpoſe are the objections of <hi>Celſus</hi> againſt the Serpent that beguiled our firſt parents. You may ſee, if you pleaſe, what anſwer is there made to him by <hi>Origen.</hi> Or, if he ſatisfie not, there be ſtore of others Fathers, and Chriſtian writers that will. Our author here <hi>(Plutarch)</hi> in his Diſcourſe, <hi>Of the ceſſation of Oracles,</hi> takes it upon him to prove that it was the opinion of divers Ancients beſides <hi>Empedocles,</hi> as <hi>Plato, Xenocrates,</hi> and others, that there were evill daemons. I wiſh he had ſet downe their owne words. I make no queſtion of the thing, that divers ancients were of that opinion, that there were evill ſpirits; but what word they uſed, becauſe we have found <hi>Plutarch</hi> before to relate the opinions of ancients not in their owne, but his words, or words of his age rather; I would gladly have knowne from themſelves. However even there <hi>Plutarch</hi> doth acknowledge that the opinion would ſeeme ſtrange to moſt men, and full (the very word here uſed) of <hi>abſurditie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] There was an ancient tradition among heathens, that certaine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>inſolent,</hi> or <hi>rebellious Gods,</hi> or <hi>daemons;</hi> (Angels, indeed:) had been caſt out of Heaven. The Originall of which tradition ſome that underſtood not, grounded it upon a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Homer</hi> (from whom, and from <hi>Heſiod,</hi> they did ordinarily fetch all their Theologie) in his <abbr>XVI.</abbr> Iliad, where <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſeverely rebukes his wife <hi>Juno,</hi> and bids her remember what ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſuffered. <hi>Celſus</hi> in <hi>Origen,</hi> out of ancient Commentators up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Homer,</hi> as is likely, doth produce a pregnant teſtimony out of <hi>Pherecydes</hi> (one of the firſt Philoſophers, of whom there is any memory extant, <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Maſter) concerning theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and their puniſhment. And it is his conceit, (or theirs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that <hi>Pherccydes</hi> underſtood <hi>Homer</hi> as they did, and grounded his words upon him. But it is a ridiculous conceit; as their allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call expoſition of <hi>Homers</hi> words is alſo, as ridiculous and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as any I have met with in that kind. Many men both later, &amp; ancient, have been deceived (as is well obſerved by learned <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenius,</hi> in his Notes upon <hi>Porphyrius</hi>) in the country of <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> making him <hi>Syrum,</hi> inſtead (a vaſt difference) of <hi>Syrium.</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> though not an Aſſyrian, yet he is one of them that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113190:15"/>are recorded by the Ancients, (<hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Numenius</hi>) to have converſed with the Hebrews, and to have been inſtructed by them. It is very likely that <hi>Plutarch</hi> here had reſpect to ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages as of others, doubtleſſe, ſo of this Philoſopher alſo. But more of him, or out of him rather, upon the laſt words. Of <hi>Empedocles</hi> there is no queſtion at all to be made, but that he had writen of theſe kind of <hi>daemons,</hi> and of their fall and baniſhment from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, very plainly and copiouſly, as may be collected out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places of <hi>Plutarch.</hi> In his Treatiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Of the inconveniencies and miſeries of taking money upon uſe,</hi> he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>certain daemons, purſued by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vengeance, and caſt out of Heaven;</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Empedocles;</hi> part of whoſe verſes he there produceth.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] <hi>Plutarch</hi> certainly doth here allude to <hi>Plato's</hi> words in his <abbr>V.</abbr> 
               <hi>De Legibus,</hi> where <hi>Plato</hi> would have all men earneſtly exhorted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. to make this their chief ſtudy, neither in time of adverſity, when croſſe <hi>daemons</hi> ariſe againſt them, nor in proſperity, when their own good <hi>daemon</hi> (ſuch was their opinion in thoſe days) ſtands for them and prevaileth, through immoderate either joy or ſorrow to misbehave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but in all fortunes and conditions to cary themſelves as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth men, according to the rules of good order and decency. His words are many: but the chiefeſt to our purpoſe are theſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>Plato,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> here, <hi>oppoſit croſſe daemons;</hi> that is in Hebrew, <hi>Satans;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of theſe evill croſſe <hi>daemons, Porphyrius,</hi> that arch-enemy of Chriſtianity, in his <hi>De Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophiâ ex Oraculis,</hi> (quoted by <hi>Theodoret, Therapeut.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> where the Latin, <hi>electorum,</hi> for, <hi>ex oraculis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, muſt be corrected) and in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and elſewhere, hath pregnant paſſages: but becauſe he lived long after Chriſt, when Heathens began in many things cunningly to temper their Philoſophy with Chriſtianity; I meddle not with him.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] It is very likely that <hi>Plutarch</hi> had a reſpect to thoſe words, (elſewhere by him excepted againſt, as we ſhall ſee afterwards) of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what it properly doth import here, may beſt be learned, as I conceive, from <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>De Poëtis legendis,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113190:16"/>where he expounds that old proverbiall ſpeech, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (that is, <hi>In the head of a Polypus, there is that which is good, and there is that which is naught</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this fiſh Polypus is pleaſant to the taſte, but it diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth ſleep with troubleſome and heterogenous</hi> (or, <hi>unnaturall) phancies,</hi> As alſo from <hi>Plautus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plautus in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t. &amp; in Rud.</note> 
               <hi>Miris modis Di ludos faciunt hominibus Miriſque exemplis: nam ſomnia in ſomnis danunt. Ne dormientes qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſinunt quieſcere.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>Miris modis, &amp;c.</hi> as before: then followes, <hi>Velut ego hac nocte hac quae praeteriit proxima, In ſomnis egi ſatis, &amp; fui homo exercitus.</hi> It is taken otherwiſe, paſſively, by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> where he defines <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in men, to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Molestiam turbulentam:</hi> though there alſo it may bear an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive conſtruction. See alſo, if you pleaſe, <hi>Oracul. Chald.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. and there <hi>Pſellus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Herodotus</hi> again, lib. <abbr>VII.</abbr> ca. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>By him,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a great army may eaſily be overthrown by a ſmall one, when God, envying them, ſhall ſend upon them a ſudden fright or thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> (as upon the <hi>Marcomanni</hi> in <hi>Marcus Antoninus</hi> his time; a famous ſtory among Chriſtian writers) <hi>through which the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy have unworthily been defeated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>without falling,</hi> properly: which puts me in mind, (and I muſt have remembred it however) of <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall. Now as we have here an ancient tradition concerning the envy and malignity of certain evill ſpirits to mankind; ſo was there among them another tradition of no leſſe antiquity, concerning the fall of man, or men, from their primitive eſtate of Angelicall happineſſe: both which traditions being put together, will make it evident, (which is a great part of our task) that the fal of <hi>Adam,</hi> as it is recorded in holy Writ, by the temptation of the Devill, was not altogether unknown unto ancient Heathens. Of this latter, (beſides <hi>Plato,</hi> and all <hi>Platonicks</hi> after him, who ſpeak of it often, but more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely, and allegorically) <hi>Tully</hi> writes in this wiſe: <hi>Ex quibus humanae vitae erroribus &amp; aerumnis fit, ut interdum veteres illi ſive va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſive in ſacris initiiſque tradendis divinae mentis interpretes, qui nos ob aliqua ſcelera ſuſcepta in vitâ ſuperiore poenarum luendarum cauſſâ, natos eſſe dixerunt, aliquid vidiſſe videantur: verumque ſit illud q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113190:16"/>eſt apud</hi> Ariſtot. <hi>ſimili nos affectos eſſe ſupplicio atque eos qui quondam, quum in praedonum Etruſcorum manus incidiſſent, crudelitate excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatâ necabantur; quorum corpora viva cum mortuis, adverſa adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis accommodata, quà aptiſſimè colligabantur; eâ noſtros animos cum corporibus copulatos, ut vivos cum mortuis eſſe conjunctos:</hi> that is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From theſe many errors</hi> (or <hi>wandrings) and miſeries of this mortall life, I am ever and anon much inclined to beleeve, that thoſe ancient, whether Prophets, or Miniſters and Interpreters of the divine will, by whom ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred rites &amp; myſteries were inſtituted; who taught that we were born and brought forth into this world to ſuffer for ſome crimes by us commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our former life; did ſpeak the truth indeed: as alſo for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſubſcribe unto that of Ariſtotles as moſt true, who writes that our puniſhment is not unlike that which was uſed by ſome Etruſcan rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (elſewhere by S.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>called</hi> Reges Etruſci; and Thuſci Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranni: <hi>Contra</hi> Creſconium Grammat. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 49. <hi>&amp; contra</hi> Parmen. l. 3. cap. ult.) <hi>who to ſhew their cruelty towards ſome who were faln into their hands, deviſed this kind of death; to fit their live bodies with other dead bodies, and to bind them up very artificially, the one oppoſite to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, face to face, and ſo of other parts: that even ſo our ſouls are cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled and joyned with our bodies, as thoſe live bodies were joyned with the dead.</hi> We owe this excellent paſſage of <hi>Tully</hi> unto S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> by whom, out of his <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> in his <abbr>IV.</abbr> book againſt <hi>Julianus</hi> the Pelagian, it is cited, and ſo preſerved; the whole book from which it was taken, ſome few fragments excepted, being ſince periſhed. <hi>Orpheus</hi> is the man intended by <hi>Tully,</hi> who was both <hi>vates,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> too, a great contriver of ſacred myſteries, who firſt, as we are told by <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Cratylus,</hi> called the body, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a tombe,</hi> or <hi>ſepulchre.</hi> This <hi>Orpheus</hi> is very ancient: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Euſebius</hi> his computation, he lived about twelve hundred years before Chriſt was born; long before <hi>Homer.</hi> There is very little of his (ſome few verſes, collected from ſeverall Authors) now extant, that is truly his: but of old, even in <hi>Platoes</hi> time, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth, there were divers counterfeit books that went under his name. <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Laertius</hi> thinks him not worthy the name of a Philoſopher. Neither doe I, if he did write indeed ſuch things, as he layeth to his charge. Now whereas thoſe ancients (<hi>Orpheus,</hi> and ſince him, <hi>Plato</hi> and others) who ſpeak of mans hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe before this life, ſeem to make man in that ſtate of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, meerly ſpirituall; a pure ſoul, I mean: this will eaſily be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113190:17"/>reconciled with the truth, if it be conſidered that the ſame Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, (<hi>Plato</hi> I am ſure) did attribute unto man, (that is, unto the ſoul of man) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>an immortall, bright, reſplendent,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>a materiall mortall body:</hi> of which t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſire to know more, may reade <hi>Syneſius</hi> in his <hi>De Inſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the Greek Scholiaſt there: as alſo <hi>Hierocles,</hi> upon <hi>Pythageras</hi> his ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes; who treat of it at large. So that according to them, the ſoule even before it was joined unto this body, was not without a body, but ſo different in qualities from this, that it ſeems it was miſtaken for another quite different, as well in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as qualities. And as for the place where <hi>this former life</hi> was, not mentioned here by <hi>Tully,</hi> but expreſſed by <hi>Plato</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to have been Heaven; we know that <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the place of our firſt Parents abode during their innocency, is even in the Scriptures taken for Heaven, ſometimes; or at leaſt, for a place of bliſſe, different from the earth: and even S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who ſharply cenſureth thoſe that turned the ſituation of Paradiſe, as it is deſcribed in the Scripture into allegories, yet himſelfe ſpareth not to ſay, that our firſt Parents in Paradiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>inhabited the earth, as a kind of Heaven;</hi> ſtyling man in the ſame place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Terreſtiall Angel.</hi> S. <hi>Baſil</hi> is yet more free in his expreſſions; and ſo are other Ancients, whom I ſhall not need to name.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] <hi>Pherecydes</hi> his words in <hi>Origen</hi> againſt <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> are theſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>Of that portion is the Tartarean portion,</hi> (or company) <hi>kept by the daughters of</hi> Boreas, Harpyes, <hi>and</hi> Thuella, (or, <hi>Tempeſt) and thither doth</hi> Jupiter <hi>cast whoever of the Gods</hi> (or <hi>Angels;</hi> which word of <hi>Angels,</hi> was not unknown to ancient Heathens, as <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and others: and <hi>Angels</hi> in the Scripture alſo, we know, are ſometimes called <hi>Gods:) doth grow inſolent;</hi> or, <hi>rebellious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with this place of <hi>Plutarch;</hi> which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that of <hi>Tully,</hi> being unqueſtionable, deſerve to be much made of by them who had rather a little genuine truth, though they labour for it, then plenty of ſpecious impoſtures. The <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byls,</hi> and <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus,</hi> we purpoſely decline to meddle with in this caſe; yea, and the <hi>Oracula Chaldaica</hi> too: which though
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113190:17"/>I doe not altogether reject, yet I am very ſuſpicious that there is in them more of <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> then his bare (as himſelfe pretends) collection.</p>
            <p>All this that hath been ſaid well pondered, S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> aſſertion, that we ſpake of before, (with little variation) that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, at the very firſt, (long before <hi>Homer</hi>) was taken in the worſt ſenſe, for an evill ſpirit; and afterwards, when evill ſpirits began to be worſhipped, (which how it happened, <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and others that have written againſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> doe ſhew) for a good ſpirit; goodneſſe and bountifulneſſe (as <hi>Tully</hi> well argues againſt <hi>Epicurus</hi>) being if not the only, yet the chiefeſt object of divine worſhip; this aſſertion, I ſay, ſo qualified, though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for want of proofs, and evidences of thoſe times, affirm it certainly true, yet certainly it may be ſuppoſed and granted not improbable. But however, take the word in either ſenſe, for <hi>a God,</hi> or for <hi>a Devill,</hi> the opinion we have ſpoken of, of the envy and malignity <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will equally, but in different reſpects ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have proceeded originally from the Scriptures. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, that the very word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God,</hi> by Greek writers, as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>Deus,</hi> by the Latins, is often uſed upon this occaſion, hath been obſerved before, and muſt here be remembred. The Text of the Scriptures that we muſt ground upon, is that unhappy confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between our firſt mother, <hi>Eve,</hi> and the ſubtill Serpent, which we therefore think fit to ſet down here at large, as we find it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the third Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. verſes of the Chapter. The words according to our laſt Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are theſe:</p>
            <p>Ver. 1. <hi>Now the Serpent was more ſubtill then any beaſt of the field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <abbr>III.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <hi>which the Lord God had made: and he ſaid unto the woman, Yea, hath God ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat of every tree of the Garden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And the woman ſaid unto the Serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midſt of the garden, God hath ſaid, Ye ſhall not cat of it, neither ſhall ye touch it, leſt ye die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>And the Serpent ſaid unto the woman, Ye ſhall not ſurely die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eies ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing good and evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113190:18"/>
            <p>Let the words, firſt in themſelves; and then compared with the event, and other circumſtances, be well conſidered, and theſe two inferences will of themſelves, as I conceive, without the help of a comment, offer themſelves to any ordinary judgement. Firſt, that the Devill doth object unto God, their Maker, envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity towards men. Secondly, that it was meer envy and malignity towards mankind, that moved the Devill, thus to ſet upon the woman, and to counſell her as he did. As I will not therefore altogether decline them, ſo neither will I trouble my ſelfe and my Reader with multiplicity of Commentators upon the place. I think it will not need; and I muſt confeſſe, I have not, at this time, many by me to look upon. We ſhall treat of thoſe two inferences in the order they were but now ſet down.</p>
            <p>Of all Ancients that have written upon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> I ſhall ever give the preeminence unto S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> for the moſt literall and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Expoſitor. Upon the 4. verſe, <hi>And the Serpent ſaid, &amp;c.</hi> he hath theſe words, (upon the fourth verſe, as I ſaid; but his words concerne the fifth rather) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>Afterwards not content to have contradicted the words of God, that he might the better make way for his impoſture, and by foiling the woman, fulfill his own deſignes, he doth traduce their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker as envious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of later Commentators, <hi>Junius,</hi> (as moſt generally received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Proteſtants) and learned <hi>Diodatus,</hi> (lately ſet out in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: I wiſh more care had been taken both in the verſion and printing) will ſuffice. <hi>Junius</hi> upon the place, <hi>Videtur enim ex multis rationibus, &amp;c. Among other arguments, which he</hi> (the Devill) <hi>uſed to perſwade them, that men were not ſo loved of God, as they thought, but hated rather, and that happineſſe was envied unto them, he brings this as the chiefeſt, becauſe they were forbidden to eat of that fruit, from which depended man's chiefeſt happineſſe, the knowledge of good &amp; evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diodatus,</hi> upon the fifth verſe, <hi>God doth know, &amp;c. He doth wreſt</hi> (I make uſe of the tranſlation ſet out) <hi>into a wrong ſenſe the name of that tree, as if it had power to conferre divine knowledge, and the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of every thing: accuſing God of envy, and provoking the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to pride and curioſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I proceed, I will by the way impart unto my Reader a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113190:18"/>certain paſſage of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> which I have often admired, and doe ſtill, as often as I think of it. The opinion being currant in his days, that God was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <hi>envious;</hi> which by the vulgar, who have little ſenſe of any other happineſſe, but ſuch as is to be found in the fruition of worldly goods, was applyed according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Metaphyſicks takes notice of both; both of the opinion, and how applyed: and as for the opinion, he doth proteſt againſt it; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>it is not poſſible it ſhould be ſo:</hi> but ſecondly, were it ſo indeed, that ſuch is the nature of God, as to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then in all probability (ſaith he) his envy doth eſpecially conſiſt in this, that he doth not afford unto men the happineſſe of perfect knowledge, and contemplation, He ſpeaketh it of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicks particularly, as abſolutely being the nobleſt of all ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; by himſelf therefore, and by others often called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Divinity.</hi> His words are not many, (as his manner is to be ſhort) but contain fully the ſubſtance of all I have ſaid; we ſhal have them afterwards upon another occaſion. I think no man hath ever laboured to any purpoſe in the ſearch of any truth, either divine, morall, or naturall; or ever obſerved with himſelfe how prone men are generally, and always have been upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both of themſelves to miſtake, and to be miſled by others; who will not acknowledge <hi>Aristotle,</hi> (though hardly cenſured by divers) as well deſerving that glorious title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(divine)</hi> as his ſo much admired maſter by ancient, both Chriſtians and Heathens, ever did, for ſo many lines. Eſpecially if to this be added his complaint in another place, that men knew ſo little of thoſe things that belonged unto God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De part. ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> profeſſing withall his readineſſe to prefer a little true Divinity, well grounded, before all humane knowledge and philoſophy.</p>
            <p>But now to returne to the words of the Devill, as they are recorded in the Scripture: though there recorded to his ſhame, and for our inſtruction; yet the Heathens that had but parcels of it, and thoſe too by tradition (whereof there be many examples in the ancient Fathers) much adulterated; no wonder if they made a contrary uſe of it, and by ſad experience finding the effects of <hi>Adam's</hi> fall, and Gods curſe; and not well informed of all particulars: the Devill alſo being as buſie with them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, as he had been with our mother <hi>Eve,</hi> to promote error and impiety: no wonder I ſay, if they made a contrary uſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113190:19"/>of what is written and recorded, and beleeved of God, many of them, as our firſt Parents (upon the Devils perſwaſion) belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Even ſince Chriſt and Chriſtianity, ſome Heathens, no vulgar men, that had read the Scripture very diligently, from theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particulars of <hi>Adam's</hi> fall, as they are there recorded, framed matter of blaſphemy; and from <hi>Moſes</hi> his words objected envy and mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnity unto that God, whoſe goodneſſe and glory <hi>Moſes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſet out. So <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> a Philoſopher, among Heathens, of prime note; by Chriſtians juſtly ſurnamed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the impious;</hi> ſpeaking of the forbidden tree, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is. <hi>Queſtionleſſe out of meer envy that tree was forbidden them, God envying men knowledge, and purpoſing that they ſhould continue fooles,</hi> (or, <hi>idiots</hi>). He is anſwered by <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> in his 38. Orat.</p>
            <p>However, the opinion was not among Heathens ſo generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but that there were ever found ſome that oppoſed it. What <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid of it, we heard but now; and before him, <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Timaeus</hi> very peremptorily concludes it that God being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>good, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, good in the higheſt degree,</hi> is his word a little before) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>he is not at all capable, or ever was of any kinde of envy.</hi> And in the <abbr>II.</abbr> of his <hi>De Repub.</hi> he is very copious, and as earneſt, as copious, upon that ſubject, that God is not the cauſe of any evill: which (with him) comes all to one as to ſay that he cannot envy. But then among them that were agreed concerning the goodneſſe of God, there was no ſmall controverſie concerning his power. For, ſaid they, were God as omnipotent, as he is good, why hath he not made all things as goodneſſe would have prompted, for the beſt? Why not the world, (thoſe that did not beleeve it ſo, as the Stoicks) eternall: men, immortall: good and vertuous, all, naturally? Hereupon the moſt (even of their wiſeſt) tell into this groſſe conceit, that God was not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>together omnipotent: that he had done what he could, and wanted power, not will, to doe all things as their own bold phancies and imaginations ſuggeſted unto them they ſhould have been done: They did put all the fault of all that was done a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſe in the world upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <hi>materiam,</hi> that God was to work upon, and was not able (ſo they) to rectifie. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. <hi>Mittamus animum ad ea quae aeterna ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, miremur, &amp;c. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>que inter illa verſantem &amp; providentem, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>madmodum qua
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113190:19"/>immortalia facere non potuit, quia materia prohibebat, &amp;c.</hi> And in his <hi>Cur bonis mala, &amp;c.</hi> cap. <abbr>V.</abbr> 
               <hi>Quare tamen Deus tam iniquus in diſtributio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fati fuit, ut bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is viris paupertatem, vulnera, &amp; acerba funera adſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beret? Non poteſt artifex mut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re materiam. Haec paſſa eſt. Quaedam &amp;c.</hi> And again in the next Chapter; <hi>At multa incidunt tristia, horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, dura toleratu. quia non poteram vos iſtis ſubducere, animos veſtros,</hi> &amp;c. So elſewhere, more then once. And ſo indeed moſt of them, Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, and others: even <hi>Epictetus</hi> himſelf (who comes neereſt to us in moſt points) in <hi>Arrianus,</hi> he ſticks not to ſay very peremptorily, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he could not certainly.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not excuſe <hi>Plato,</hi> though ſome have taken great pains to doe it; how ridiculous ſoever the opinion may ſeem, his words are plain, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <hi>materiaprima,</hi> as eternall as God himſelfe, did concurre with him, to the making of all things: and that God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſo he ſpeaks; and <hi>Alcinous</hi> out of him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that is, <hi>Did his beſt,</hi> that all things might be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for the beſt.</hi> Sometimes he ſpeaks very doubtfully. I confeſſe, and cannot be excuſed from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting himſelf (as by <hi>Plutarch</hi> is well obſerved in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) in words, at leaſt, whatever he intended: which alſo made the Ancients not to agree among themſelves about his opinion. <hi>Dio. Laertius</hi> acknowledges but two <hi>principia,</hi> according to <hi>Plato; Plutarch, Apuleius, Alcinou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and others, reckon three. And of them that reckon three, ſome give them farre different appellations from thoſe that others do: So that in very deed, let a man be never ſo well verſed in <hi>Plato,</hi> he ſhall find it a matter of great obſcurity &amp; difficulty abſolutely to determine what was his opinion. However, what we have now cited out of him, he hath in divers places.</p>
            <p>Others againe there were, who took upon them to maintain, as the goodneſſe, ſo the omnipotency of God, as <hi>Simplicius,</hi> (one of the later, but not inferiour unto many Philoſophers) in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries upon <hi>Ariſtotle De Coelo,</hi> where he hath a long conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Alexander Aphrodiſienſis</hi> about it. Whether all his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſolutions (in point of humane reaſon, I mean, by which only he goes) be ſatisfactory or no; eſpecially, where he handleth the point of morall evill, why permitted by God; becauſe it is not my purpoſe here to engage my ſelfe, (elſewhere I may perchance) in that obſcure and intricate Argument, I muſt leave to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and judicious Reader, who will not repent him his labour if he read him attentively. All I ſhall ſay of it is this, that what he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113190:20"/>anſwereth concerning morall evill, is the very ſame that is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by divers ancient Fathers upon this occaſion: but extreamly diſliked, ſlighted, and ſcoffed at by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Treatiſe, <hi>Of common notions againſt the Stoicks.</hi> Indeed as <hi>Plutarch</hi> relates that matter from <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> it cannot but ſeem very abſurd and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: But he that ſhall reade <hi>Simplicius</hi> not upon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> only, but upon <hi>Epictetus</hi> his <hi>Enchiridion</hi> alſo, where he handles it (in two or three places) very largely, may perchance be of another opinion, and think that <hi>Plutarch</hi> might have ſpared ſome of his jeſts, and rather have taken more paines to underſtand the ſtate of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion better then it ſeems he did.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Chryſippus</hi> his opinion <hi>Aulus Gell.</hi> alſo hath a Chapter in his <hi>Noctes Atticae,</hi> which in the latter Editions of <hi>Aulus Gell.</hi> is ſet out as imperfect, or defective in the beginning: it was not ſo in the old Editions; and why it ſhould be ſo in the new I know no reaſon, but that, as I conceive, thoſe that firſt ſo ſet him out did not underſtand him, and choſe rather (as many in that eaſe to the great prejudice of good Authors) to place the defect upon the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, then to acknowledge it in themſelves. I ſhall be very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beſtow ſome paines to do that good Author ſome right, who hath taken ſo many paines to benefit poſterity; and we ſhall finde it to our purpoſe too. Nevertheleſſe, becauſe all men are not for that kinde of learning, it ſhall make no further interruption here, but ſhall be added at the end. The place of <hi>Gellius</hi> that we mean, is <hi>lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>VI.</abbr> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Homines feciſſe dicitur, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, beſides theſe we have ſpoken of, there were yet others, who upon grounds of naturall reaſon ſtood for the goodneſſe both and omnipotency of God as peremp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orily as any; yet durſt not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame grounds of naturall reaſon take upon themſelves to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all objections againſt their opinion, which (their naturall reaſon) they modeſtly acknowledged weak and deſective, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of ſuch high myſteries and ſpeculations. <hi>Plotinus</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, as I remember, (I might ſay <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> too, but that what he ſaith of the defect of humane reaſon, which he compares to the eyes of Bats, is upon another occaſion) hath an excellent paſſage or two to that purpoſe. <hi>Antoninus</hi> (a great and glorious Monarch in his dayes; by many, as deſervedly as ever Heathen was, both for his learning and goodneſſe, ſurnamed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The Philoſopher</hi>) hath I am ſure, which may be read in his <hi>Meditations concerning himſelfe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113190:20"/>lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>II.</abbr> 
               <hi>n.</hi> 8. but eſpecially, <hi>lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>XII.</abbr> 
               <hi>n.</hi> 4. How ſo many came to pitch upon this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>materiam,</hi> and partly to joyn, partly to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it unto God in the creation, might eaſily be conceived if we compare what divers of them write of it with the words of <hi>Moſes, Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2. of the Chaos, which very Chaos ſome of them called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> Though they ſay not altogether what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, and added to it much; yet a man may in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s words ſee ſome ground for their errours. In ſo obſcure a ſubject (<hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is in the Text, and <hi>caligo</hi> is the word uſed by ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the <hi>Chaos</hi>) they might eaſily miſtake him; they eſpecially that had him but by tradition. But I will ſay no more of it here, becauſe it is but upon the by.</p>
            <p>And ſo much concerning the originall of the opinion, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Daemon,</hi> or, <hi>The Daemon</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>the Deity,</hi> in the language and more clear expreſſion of divers others, as by divers examples hath appeared) is of an envious nature.</p>
            <p>There be other places of Scripture, I know, (beſides that of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi>) which upon this occaſion, and not impertinently perchance, might have been conſidered of. As for example, thoſe Ironicall words (though poſſibly not Ironically taken by all that might light upon them) of Almighty God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> 22, 23. <hi>And the Lord God ſaid, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good or evill. And now leſt he put forth his hand and take alſo of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever. Therefore the Lord God ſent him forth from the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Eden, &amp;c.</hi> And againe, thoſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 
               <abbr>XI.</abbr> 6. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Behold, the people is one, and they have all one language, and this they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to do: and now nothing will be reſtrained from them which they have imagined to do, &amp;c.</hi> But eſpecially, that ambiguous ſignification of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which as it ſignifies <hi>to be jealous (Exod.</hi> 
               <abbr>XX.</abbr> 5. XXXIV. 14. and elſewhere frequently:) ſo <hi>Geneſis</hi> 
               <abbr>XXXI.</abbr> 1. and elſewhere, <hi>to envie.</hi> But ſince we have, as I conceive, ſufficiently diſcovered and laid open the main ſpring of the errour, I ſhall be leſſe ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about the Riverets and ſmaller ſtreams.</p>
            <p>We will now ſuppoſe that <hi>Daemon</hi> was originally taken for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill or Evill-Spirit. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> This ſuppoſition is not without ſome probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as hath been ſaid. But if that will not be granted, we are ſure however that ſince Chriſt it was ſo taken by many Heathens; and that even before, long before Chriſt, there was an opinion among Heathens of certaine envious Spirits or Devils that did ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113190:21"/>againſt men, to doe them what miſchiefe they could. Now how conſonant it is to the Scriptures to adſcribe all temporall evils to the malice and envy of the Devill, as the firſt and originall cauſe, is ſo apparently obvious, as little ſhall need to bee ſaid about it.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Through envy of the devill came death into the world,</hi> ſaith the author of the booke of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> (Chap. 11. ver. ult.) attributed unto <hi>Solomon;</hi> In which words by <hi>death</hi> muſt be underſtood not bare death onely, but all the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it: all the changes &amp; chances to which this our mortality is lyable; which make our very life, (as divers ancient heathens have taught) rather a daily death, then life, properly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. that is, <hi>Behold the envy, and manifold,</hi> (or <hi>deep) ſubtiltie of the wicked daemon. For when he ſaw man created to higheſt honour, and little inferior to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp;c.</hi> The word he uſeth here, and ſome lines after, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but afterwards both here, and upon the ſeventh verſe, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. S. <hi>Baſil</hi> in his <hi>Homilie,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That God is not the cauſe of evills,</hi> hath both the words together. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Being</hi> (the Devill) <hi>the receptacle of all wickedneſſe, he laboured of envy alſo. Our honour became an eyeſore unto him.</hi> So <hi>Baſil</hi> there: but in his <abbr>XXI.</abbr> Homilie, <hi>Vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> (ſo inſcribed) <hi>places of Scripture,</hi> having occaſion to ſpeake of <hi>envy</hi> in generall, he falls upon this particular of the devills envy, and mans ruine through it, and handles it very rhetorically, So <hi>Gregor, Nyſſen,</hi> as pathetically, though not ſo largely, in his, <hi>De vita Moſis.</hi> Divers more might be added. Hardly ſhall we finde any Ancients that either ſpeake of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, or his poſterities miſeries in this life, but have a touch of the Devils envie. As for moderne authors, in ſo obvious, and ſo unqueſtionable a ſubject among all Chriſtians, I ſhall for beare their teſtimonies, and proceed to other matter.</p>
            <p>We have preſumed that time out of mind ſuch an opinion was among the heathens concerning this <hi>invidia daemonis,</hi> the ſubject of our Diſcourſe. We think we have ſaid enough to make it probable. VVe will now ſee what can be ſaid againſt it: to wit, whether his Name can be produced that firſt either ſaid it, or was obſerved to ſay it among heathens: which though it might, yet it doth not follow but that originally it might be from the Scriptures, ſince that it may as probably be ſuppoſed, whoever that firſt was, by ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113190:21"/>many ages either neerer, or farther from the ſpring, that he had it from the Scriptures, which all antiquity beleeved that <hi>Pherecydes, Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and divers others in their times by travelling into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and other farre countries, and there converſing with ſome of the Iewiſh nation, had ſome knowledge of. Nevertheleſſe, to give the reader all ſatisfaction I can in this point, I will (as we promiſed before) ſee what can be ſaid about it. There be two, (more, it may be; but two that I remember) who ſeeme to make <hi>Herodotus</hi> the firſt: <hi>Plutarch,</hi> ſufficiently knowne unto all men, and <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> who hath commented, or rather abbreviated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the ancient innumerous Commentators upon <hi>Homer. Plutarch,</hi> among other many tractats, in that part of his workes, which is called, <hi>his Morals,</hi> hath one intitled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Concerning the malignity of</hi> Herodotus; and in that tractat, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things, as well became him, he takes notice of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity towards the Gods: His words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>In the perſon of</hi> Solon <hi>he reproacheth the Gods in theſe words: Doſt thou, ó</hi> Croeſus, <hi>conſult me about humane affaires, who know full well that all Deitie is of an envious and unpeaceable</hi> (Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that takes pleaſure to disturbe, &amp; to create troubles:</hi> we have ſpoken of the word before) <hi>diſpoſition.] For what himſelfe conceited of the Gods, in fathering it upon</hi> Solon, <hi>he addes malignity to blasphemy.</hi> This is all he ſaith of it; and it is very obſervable he ſaith no more. Firſt, that whereas <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> foure ſeverall times at leaſt, upon ſeverall occaſions doth ſo blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, he ſhould take notice but of one. And ſecondly, that he ſhould ſay nothing (copious enough, if not exuberant upon moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars) againſt the opinion it ſelfe by way of confutation, and in vindication of his gods; knowing well, that if <hi>Herodotus</hi> were the firſt, he was not the onely that had ſaid it. The truth is, it is not likely that <hi>Plutarch</hi> did beleeve <hi>Herodotus</hi> to have been the firſt; neither indeed doth he directly ſay it, though his words might ſeeme to import as much. But beſides this, <hi>Plutarch</hi> was conſcious unto himſelfe, that himſelfe had ſaid as much, or little leſſe. There be divers places to be found in him, that might be preſſed to this purpoſe: I ſhall inſtance in one. In his <hi>Conſolation to Apollonius, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip King of Macedon,</hi> (ſaith he: we had ſomewhat of this <hi>Philip</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) <hi>upon the hearing of three ſeverall happy tydings, all in one day, lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his hands unto heaven, he ſaid, O daemon, unto theſe my good haps, oppoſe I pray thee, ſome tolerable misfortune: Knowing that ſuch is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113190:22"/>of fortune, to envy great ſucceſſes.</hi> So <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Herodotus</hi> doth; but how common and ordinary it is to all ſorts of writers, (profeſſed Epicureans and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts excepted) to uſe the word <hi>fortune</hi> in ſtead of <hi>God,</hi> is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, and hath been, even by heathens, obſerved. We ſhall, not long after, quote a paſſage of <hi>Diod. Siculus,</hi> where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fortune;</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Gods,</hi> are apparently in one and the ſame ſentence, put for the ſame. Perhaps the generality of the aſſertion, that <hi>all Deity, &amp;c.</hi> was it that <hi>Plutarch</hi> excepted againſt in <hi>Herodotus:</hi> &amp; ſo he might be the onely perchance that ſo generally, and peremptorily (take them both together) doth affirme it. Certainely, whoſoever was the firſt that durſt publickly ſo blaſpheme; ſo eaſily to entertaine, and ſo often to inculcate the blaſphemy as <hi>Herodotus</hi> doth, even this was enough to evince his impiety; and it was not, I beleeve, without ſome providence, that his <hi>malignity,</hi> in generall, ſhould be ſo ſifted, and as it were, publickly in the eyes of all men, and that by the heathens themſelves cited, arraigned, and condemned; (as it is there in that accurate <hi>Invective,</hi> or <hi>Indictment</hi> rather:) who had ſhewed ſo little ingenuity in the cauſe of God.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Plutarch,</hi> ſo <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> he alſo ſeemeth to make <hi>Herodotus</hi> the firſt author of this blaſphemy; but ſeemeth onely. His words upon the laſt of the Iliads, are theſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. <hi>The Poet making,</hi> or <hi>ſetting out,</hi> or <hi>bringing in the gods,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>generally, as often hath been obſerved, adſcribes unto them ſuch affections, as men in ſuch caſes would probably be affected with. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which this is one, that thoſe who in other things are far eminent, would not have thoſe of a lower condition to be equall unto them in point of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: whether,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>becauſe they ſpight them; or, as</hi> Herodotus <hi>would ſay,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>becauſe they envy; or for ſome other cauſe.</hi> I tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the words as they muſt be read, &amp; not as they are printed (in the Baſil. edition, at leſt) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: of which no ſenſe can be made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, imply but one thing, and it is likely ſome either Poet, or proſe author upon this very ſubject, had the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. However, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being the word (and the onely, as I take it) often u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Herodotus</hi> upon this occaſion it can be no wonder if <hi>Euſtath,</hi> (or whoever; ſome ancienter Commentator in him perchance) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now occaſion to uſe it himſelfe, name him: thereby rather al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding to his word, as I conceive, then to his opinion, as either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to him, or derived from him.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113190:22"/>
            <p>But may not <hi>Euſtathius</hi> be thought to derive it here rather from <hi>Homer</hi> him ſelfe? I think, not: for all that can be made of his words is not that <hi>Homer</hi> doth directly ſay ſo; but this, that the Poet doth adſcribe ſuch affections unto the Gods, as may be thought to proceed from ſuch a cauſe. <hi>Homer</hi>'s owne words in that place are theſe;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—</l>
               </q> That is, <hi>How have the Gods appointed unto miſerable men, to live in grief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is no more then the Scripture ſaith in divers places, not of <hi>gods,</hi> but of <hi>God:</hi> and yet the cauſe, nevertheleſſe, according to the Scriptures, not envy, but juſtice, and juſt judgement, yea, and <hi>mercy,</hi> in ſome reſpect; as heathens themſelves, upon this very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, acknowledge. Beſides, it is well knowne, that <hi>Homer</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, (we ſhall have occaſion to produce his words upon the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Aul. Gell.</hi>) brings in <hi>Jupiter</hi> complaining of the iniquity of men, who lay the cauſe of their miſeries upon the Gods.</p>
            <p>But were it ſo that <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Euſtathius</hi> ſhould directly ſay it either of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> or <hi>Homer;</hi> yet there would be other Ancients found of no leſſe anthority then they, to contradict them. <hi>Simonides,</hi> an ancient Greek Poet, was ſince <hi>Homer</hi> indeed, but before <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> one full century of yeares, at leaſt. Now <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, ſpeaking <hi>obiter</hi> of this matter, and in the very termes as <hi>Herodotus</hi> doth, he quotes this <hi>Simonides,</hi> and might be thought to make him the firſt author. But he doth not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he takes notice of the ſaying from <hi>Simonides</hi> the Poet, indeed, and becauſe from none but him, diſapproving the ſaying, he is content to ſay, that Poets will lye. That no body ſaid it before him he doth not write, neither will it follow. Laſtly, how eaſily either <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or any other, in caſe they had ſpoken more peremptorily, might be miſtaken in this point, ſince neither all bookes were extant in any age, that have formerly been written, be it the happieſt age that ever was; nor all that are extant, likely to come to any one mans knowledge, be he never ſo carefull and curious, I leave it further to be conſidered. <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> words in Engliſh (thoſe memorable words we mentioned before) are theſe: <hi>Therefore it may well be thought that the poſſeſſion</hi> (or <hi>purchaſe) of this ingenuous noble ſcience</hi> (the Metaphyſicks) <hi>doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto men: For the nature of man, in many reſpects, is ſlaviſh: ſo that according to</hi> Simonides <hi>this bleſſedneſſe doth peculiarly belong unto God; neither is it fit for man to ſeeke that ſcience which is above him</hi> [or <hi>which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113190:23"/>is not granted unto him.</hi> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, as I conceive, ſuch trajections being very uſuall, to <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> eſpecially; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] <hi>And if that of the Poet be true, that God can envie, I think it appliable to this eſpecially:</hi> [Gr. <hi>It is probable that it ſo fals out in this eſpecially:</hi>] <hi>whence it will follow, that all men are unfortunate</hi> [Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: he alludes to thoſe verſes of <hi>Euripides,</hi> as I take it, cited by him in his Ethicks, <hi>lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>VI.</abbr> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which is divinely confuted by him in the ſaid Ethicks, the 7. &amp; 8. Chapters of the <abbr>X.</abbr> Book] <hi>who aſpire to ſuch excellency. But neither is it a thing poſſible that God ſhould envie, but according to the Proverbe, Poets will faine many things</hi> (or <hi>often lye:) neither ought we</hi> (though but men, and not ſo capable of it as of other things, that is,) <hi>to make more reckoning of any other ſcience then of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> may give light to an obſcure paſſage of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> who in his fifth <hi>Stromat.</hi> having diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at large, and to that end, brought proofes out of the Scripture alſo, That God had not revealed the truth unto men, but in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and allegories, <hi>in dreams, and ſymboles:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. that is, <hi>not out of envie, ſince that to phanſie God ſubject to paſſions,</hi> (ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt here be rendred, not as it is tranſlated, <hi>patibilis:</hi> in which ſenſe it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <abbr>XXVI.</abbr> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 23.) <hi>is impious, but, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with my main ſubject, the originall of that opinion of ancient Heathens, <hi>De invidia Daemonis.</hi> I muſt now remember an obſervation of the ſame Ancients, ſpoken of at the beginning, concerning unuſuall, overſwelling proſperity; for which there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficient ground (in ordinary conſtruction) upon daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, the opinion <hi>de invidia Daemonis</hi> (eſpecially by them of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter times from the beginning, who were leſſe acquainted with ancient traditions) may be thought as well to be grounded upon the ſame experience. This tradition, <hi>de invidia Daemonis,</hi> being once up, and generally received among men, though originally grounded, as we have ſaid, and derived from the particulars of <hi>Adams</hi> fall: yet afterwards, when the revolution of many Ages had partly adulterated, and partly altogether obliterated the truth of things, it was applyed by men diverſly, according to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinions men had of the Deity, and as they ſtood differently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected (ſome placing happineſſe in knowledge, ſome in greatneſſe,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113190:23"/>in pleaſure ſome, and ſome in ſome other thing) to the things of this world. But the moſt generall application of it being, as we have ſaid, and partly ſhewed, to all eminent worldly proſperity; it will be requiſite therefore, and conſequent to our firſt intention to ſhew, what further probable grounds (beſides experience) either from certain words of Scripture, ſeemingly importing ſome ſuch thing; or from relations of Scripture Hiſtories (from which, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers prove, moſt of their fables were derived) ancient Heathens might have for this obſervation. Paſſages of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which by them might eaſily be drawne to that ſenſe, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: the effect of all which is by Chriſt compriſed in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall exalt himſelfe, ſhall be abaſed: and he that ſhall humble himſelfe, ſhall be exalted, Matth.</hi> XXIII. <hi>v.</hi> 12. There was a ſaying among ancient Grecians, attributed by them unto <hi>Aeſope,</hi> as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it: but certainly, whether by <hi>Aeſope</hi> firſt, or any other, taken out of the Scriptures originally, that it was the proper work of God, and his chiefeſt occupation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>To abaſe the things that are high, and to exalt thoſe that are low.</hi> It is thus expreſſed by <hi>Euripides:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is,
<note place="margin">Euripid. in Troad.</note> 
               <hi>I ſee the Gods,</hi> (or <hi>the wayes of the Gods) thoſe things which are low, they exalt aloft,</hi> (Gr. <hi>they make to tower on high) and thoſe that are eminent</hi> (or <hi>highly priſed) they caſt down.</hi> See if you pleaſe <hi>Iob</hi> 
               <abbr>V.</abbr> 11. and <abbr>XL.</abbr> 10, 11, 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> CXIII. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <abbr>I</abbr> 
               <hi>Sam.</hi> 
               <abbr>II.</abbr>3, 4, 5. &amp;c. all pregnant places to this purpoſe as I take it, and many more may be found: but of all, I conceive that of <hi>Eſay</hi> concerning <hi>Tyre,</hi> to be moſt emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; <hi>Tyre,</hi> that once renowned City, whoſe Colonies, <hi>pene toto orbe diffuſae,</hi> had ſpread themſelves throughout the whole World almoſt, as ancient Hiſtorians teſtifie: <hi>Carthage,</hi> the once Imperiall City of <hi>Africa,</hi> (that ſo long conteſted with <hi>Rome</hi> about the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of the World) and divers other great Townes owing their originall unto it. Of this <hi>Tyre</hi> the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay <abbr>XXIII.</abbr> 8, 9</note> among many others, hath theſe words, (I muſt crave leave that I may ſet them down in their originall language, becauſe of the elegancy,) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 8, <hi>Who hath taken this counſell againſt Tyre, the crowning [City]
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113190:24"/>whoſe Merchants are Princes, whoſe traffiquers are the honourable of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed it, to ſtaine the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the honourable of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>Tyre</hi> were the occaſion and principall object (and well it might then be for the pride and ſtatelineſſe of it) of the words, yet the ſentence I take to be generall, extending to all, as times, ſo places equally.</p>
            <p>I have no thought that ever <hi>Lucretius,</hi> a notorious Epicurean, had any knowledge of the holy Scriptures; and his thoughts I dare ſay were farre enough from what the Prophet, or the Holy Ghoſt by him, aimed at in theſe words: yet it cannot be denied that he is an excellent Poet, and that his words come very near to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſenſe of thoſe of the Prophet, where he ſaith,
<q>
                  <l>Vſque adeò res humanas vis abdita quaedum
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lucret. I ib.</hi> 
                        <abbr>v.</abbr>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obterit, &amp; pulchros faſceis ſaevaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſecures,</l>
                  <l>Proculcare, &amp; ludibrio ſibi habere videtur.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Of Scripture Hiſtories, that of holy <hi>Iobs</hi> more then ordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, as it is recorded in the firſt Chapter; and the ſudden alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which upon Satan (there ſaid to have <hi>appeared among the ſons of God</hi>) his wicked and malitious ſuggeſtion and crimination enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo ancient and ſo remarkable, as it cannot be conceived that it ſhould altogether be unknown unto them, ſo what they might ignorantly inferre upon it, they that are verſed in their mytholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies may eaſily gueſſe. Through the inſtigation of the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (as is expreſſed <abbr>I</abbr> 
               <hi>Chron.</hi> 
               <abbr>XXI.</abbr> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 1.) <hi>David</hi> King of Iſrael, would needs have <hi>the people numbred:</hi> whereupon Gods wrath and a great plague upon the people of God enſued. Of this there is no queſtion, the Text is plaine, that God was angry, and the people plagued; but what was <hi>Davids</hi> crime, doth not ſo clearly appear by the Text; neither are Expoſitors of one minde about it. <hi>Joſephus</hi> of old, and ſome Rabbins ſince him, make this to have been <hi>Davids</hi> treſpaſſe, becauſe he did not impoſe the redemption mony <hi>(half a ſicle)</hi> commanded by God, <hi>Exod.</hi> XXX. <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13. upon ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Learned <hi>Diodatus</hi> his opinion (ſlipt over in the late Engliſh Edition of his Notes) upon <abbr>II</abbr> 
               <hi>Sam. c.</hi> 24. is, that <hi>David</hi> (beſides ſome other concurring provocations) offended in that he <hi>did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the law concerning the right age, to wit,</hi> 20 <hi>years, from which and upwards, the people was to be numbred, Exo,</hi> 
               <abbr>XXX.</abbr> 14. <hi>Num.</hi> 
               <abbr>I.</abbr> 2.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113190:24"/>
            <p>So they: but the current opinion of Interpreters, ſaith <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> upon the place, is, that <hi>elatio animi</hi> and <hi>ſuperbia,</hi> was his fault. <hi>God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>had given him peace. He had got a Catalogue of his valiant men, and now he ſets his minde upon it, to know the number of his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Subjects.</hi> So Rev. Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi> alſo, <hi>Quando tuleris ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam filio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Iſr. &amp;c. When thou takeſt the ſumme of the children of Iſrael:</hi> that is, <hi>When thou ſhalt number them, either by me commanded, or of thy ſelfe when thou ſhalt think it expedient for the publicke good. For the numbring of the people upon ſuch occaſions was not diſpleaſing unto God, which nevertheleſſe in</hi> David <hi>for other cauſes was reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Not certainly, as ſome Hebrews are of opinion, becauſe he took no care for the tribute money, which was to be payed unto God: this could not be the reaſon why Joab diſſwaded him from it: but becauſe he ſaw that it was not done out of a good minde, but rather out of vanity and pride, as may appear from the whole context,</hi> 
               <abbr>II</abbr> 
               <hi>Sam.</hi> XXIV. So he. And this indeed, all circumſtances, as he ſaith, of the ſtory well weighed, will appear the moſt probable conjecture: multitude of ſubjects, (according to that of <hi>Solomon, In the multitude of people is the Kings honour, but in the want of people is the deſtruction of the Prince, Prov.</hi> XIV. 28.) being a very likely object of a Princes pride and carnall confidence. Now if pride was the cauſe both of this anger and plague, and the matter ſo publickly noyſed and conſtrued; it is very likely that the fame of ſo memorable a judgement (the ſudden o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and ceſſation of it, if not the plague it ſelfe, being appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently miraculous) ſpread it ſelf to many parts of the world, then inhabited by Heathens. Of Ambaſſadours ſent by the Princes of <hi>Babylon</hi> to enquire of <hi>the wonder in the land</hi> vouchſafed unto King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> in confirmation of his recovery and prolongation of dayes by the immediate hand of God, we are told expreſly <abbr>II</abbr> 
               <hi>Chr.</hi> XXXII. <hi>v.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>And ſince I have mentioned this of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> I cannot paſſe by, being ſo pertinent to our purpoſe, <hi>Iſidore Peluſiota,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſid. Peluſ. Epiſt. l.</hi> 11. <hi>Ep.</hi> 74.</note> that elegant and witty Writer, his obſervation concerning him, as it followeth: [<hi>In the reign of King Hezekiah, the King of Perſia came with all his power against Ieruſalem, and was overthrowne by a divine miracle, one of the greatest that ever was. Whereupon</hi> Hezekiah <hi>being puffed up, and now through immoderate joy entertaining thoughts of himſelf above a man, God with a ſickneſſe, as with a bridle curbed him, to compoſe his ſwelling minde, and to make him ſenſible of his naturall frailty, and to cure
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113190:25"/>him of that diſeaſe which his ſoule had contracted through exceſſe of joy.</hi>] So <hi>Iſidore:</hi> and it is in that Epiſtle that he writes of <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> the <hi>Theban</hi> Commander, of whom we had ſomewhat in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. What ground this <hi>Iſidore</hi> might have either from the Scriptures themſelves (by way of inference:) or from tradition for this obſervation, I know not: But in my judgement, <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> miraculous (in ſome circumſtances of it) recovery of that ſickneſſe he ſpeaks of, and upon it, his vaine oſtentation of all his treaſures and pretious things in all his Kingdome before thoſe Ambaſſadours whom forein Princes had ſent to congratulate him, ſo particularly noted in the Scripture, <abbr>II</abbr> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> 
               <abbr>XX.</abbr> 12, 13, &amp;c. and upon this oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that dreadfull denunciation of future heavie judgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his poſterity, do ſufficiently evince, that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (after his recovery at leaſt) did forget himſelf; and that God in mercy to him did uſe means to recall him, before he ſhould be too far gone. Theſe words (beſides the ſtory) ſeem to me to import as much:
<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>II</abbr> Chr. <abbr>XXXII.</abbr> 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>But Hezekiah rendred not againe according to the benefit done unto him: for his heart was lifted up, therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon Judah and Jeruſalem. Notwithstanding, Hezekiah humbled himſelf for the pride of his heart (both he and the inhabitants of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem) ſo that the wrath of the Lord came not upon them in the dayes of Hezekiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like paſſages of Scripture might, and did as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, at the firſt (in part) occaſion that obſervation of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, of the danger of more then ordinary worldly proſperity. But their ignorance of the Scriptures, or want rather of perfect knowledge of them, made them upon this obſervation to inferre (in the manner I have ſaid before) this wicked and impious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that God was of a maligne and envious diſpoſition. I ſee here a large field open, but I will not enter into it, as not being within the compaſſe either of my undertaking (which was only to ſhew the originall of the opinion:) or my leiſure and opportunity at this time. I ſhall only take notice of two reaſons which are touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by ancient Heathens, not Philoſophers I do not meane, who have written of purpoſe, and more generally concerning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: but Hiſtorians, upon the by, and in this very ſubject of either great proſperity ſuddenly blaſted, or ſorrowes intermingled with joyes; their reaſons, as I conceive, being very agreeable to the doctrine of the ſacred Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113190:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herodotus,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> in one of thoſe places where he chargeth God with envie, among other expreſſions to that purpoſe, hath theſe words: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>That God will not end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re that any other ſhould thinke well of himſelfe, but himſelfe.</hi> Indeed it cannot be denied that the holy Scriptures both of the Old and New Teſtament do ſet out God unto us, as very jealous of his honour in that particular, in whoſe eyes nothing is more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abominable, <hi>then high looks, and high thoughts;</hi> who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf againſt all pride and ſelf-conceit (in point of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome eſpecially) as direct invaſion, or uſurpation upon his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty. I do not remember that God is ſaid in the Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to reſiſt</hi> any other ſinners but the proud. <hi>He diſappointeth the deviſes of the crafty,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Job; ſo that their hands cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their enterpriſe. He taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job V. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>and the courſell of the froward is carried headlong.</hi> This, I think, no man ſhould wonder at; but rather wonder that any mortall men ſhould ſo much forget themſelves, their beginning, their end; their frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, mentall and corporall, whileſt they live; as to grudge God, their maker (who of meer duſt and clay hath made them what they are:) this prerogative of being The only wiſe: either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching his goodneſſe, becauſe men are but men, and not Gods; or conteſting with his wiſdome, as very Gods themſelves, and not men. Such men (prodigies of ingratitude) have been, and are yet in the world. <hi>Eſt aliquid quo ſapiens antecedat Deum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. <hi>Ep.</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>Ille naturae beneficio, non ſuo ſapiens eſt. Ecce res magna, habere imbecillitatem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, ſecuritatem Dei.</hi> And againe, <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Id. Ep.</hi> 73.</note> 
               <hi>quò antecedit virum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num? diutius bonus eſt. Sapiens nihilo ſe minoris aestimat, quod virtutes ejus spatio breviore clauduntur.</hi> And few lines after, <hi>Deus non vincit ſapientem foelicitate, etiamſi vincat aetate: Non eſt virtus major, quae largior.</hi> Such was the language, not of <hi>Seneca</hi> only, but of thoſe wiſe men (not of all, ſome were aſhamed of it, but of moſt) that were known from other Philoſophers, by the name of Stoicks. I could inſtance in ſome of our dayes alſo, who though profeſſing Chriſtianity, come not ſhort of theſe (if they have not exceeded them) in their way of boaſting: but I will leave them to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of poſterity. Now if men, notwithſtanding ſo many threats, and ſo many judgements againſt the proud and haughty, be never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſo apt to take upon themſelves: What then (it is S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> obſervation ſomewhere,) would they do, if God did uſe no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113190:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch means, no ſuch examples to refrain them? So that upon due conſideration, what in the judgement of blinde and corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeemed envie and malignity, will appear mercy: being uſed by God as a profitable medicine or antidote againſt the greateſt and moſt dangerous infection of the ſoul: and to teach men (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, even in the judgement of divers Heathens, conſiſts their chiefeſt as wiſdome, ſo happineſſe) wholly to depend of God, and in all things to acknowledge him <hi>all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jobs</hi> words that we but now mentioned (or others to the ſame purpoſe) are in <hi>Eſay</hi> alſo, <hi>Eſay</hi> 
               <abbr>XLIV</abbr>. 25. and <abbr>XXIX</abbr>. 14. Out of one of them <hi>Homer</hi> it may be (or ſome other before <hi>Homer,</hi> of whom he might borrow them) had his: for they containe the very ſenſe, the words are theſe (it is a woman, <hi>Penelope,</hi> that ſpeaks.)</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Homer <hi>Od.</hi> Ψ</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So much of the firſt reaſon. It is <hi>Herodotus</hi> his reaſon, that God of purpoſe doth often confound the (carnall) wiſdome and glory of men leſt they ſhould think too well of themſelves. So far <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> is in the right, and agrees well with the Scriptures themſelvs: But his inference upon it (even in the judgement of more ſober humane reaſon) moſt wicked and abſurd, That therefore God doth envie to men their happineſſe and proſperity.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon is given by <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> in his <abbr>III.</abbr> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> 
               <hi>Biblioth. Hiſt.</hi> where having diſcourſed at large of the manifold bleſſedneſſe of <hi>Arabia Foelix;</hi> and particularly of the excellent odours and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes that Woods and other parts of the Countrey do yeild, hee addes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>Nevertheleſſe God</hi> (ſo I tranſlate here the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>hath not afforded unto men any intire happines, without ſome blemiſh</hi> (or <hi>envie,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) <hi>but to theſe his bleſſings he hath annexed ſomewhat that is hurtfull, which might ſerve to admoniſh them, who through continuance of worldly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are wont to grow into a contempt of the Gods.</hi> Here firſt I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that whereas this ſeemeth to contradict what by ſome others is affirmed, that men are worſe in times of extremity; it is eaſie to reconcile them by diſtinguiſhing, as of degrees of temporall croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo of differences of tempers and diſpoſitions, ſome naturally
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113190:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>being better able with patience to bear, though much more adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; then they can proſperity, with moderation and ſobriety: and ſome on the contrary, but this by the way onely. That plenty and long proſperity would be apt to beget pride, and impiety, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of religion, the Iſraelites, and in them, all men generally were forewarned by God himſelfe, Deut. <abbr>VIII.</abbr> from the tenth verſe, to the end of that Chapter. <hi>Clem. Alexand.</hi> in the <abbr>V.</abbr> of his <hi>Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata,</hi> not farre from the beginning, hath collected out of ancient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſome paſſages, which ſay almoſt the ſame. But let me give this caution to thoſe that ſhall have recourſe unto him about this matter firſt to read the paſſage of <hi>Thucydides</hi> in <hi>Thucydides</hi> (lib. <abbr>III.</abbr> in <hi>Cleo</hi>'s ſpeech) himſelfe: which in <hi>Clemens</hi> is printed very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And ſo may <hi>Philiſtus,</hi> who doth ſo imitate <hi>Thucydides,</hi> as that he doth almoſt tranſcribe him <hi>verbatim,</hi> be underſtood, his words, for want either of this caution, or of diligence, are much miſtaken by the Latine Interpreter. But to proceed, That troubles and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on the other ſide, are apt (of themſelves, for divers circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may alter the caſe) to ſtirre up zeale and devotion, and to bring a man to himſelfe, is not onely obſerved by ſacred writers, and by Philoſophers, but even by them acknowledged that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Atheiſme, or (which comes all to one, as <hi>Tully</hi> of old hath proved) Epicuriſme: as by <hi>Lucretius,</hi> in theſe words,
<q>
                  <l>—Multoque in rebus acerbis</l>
                  <l>Acriùs advertunt animos ad relligionem.</l>
                  <l>Quò magis in dub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is hominem ſpectare periclis</l>
                  <l>Convenit, adverſiſque in rebus noſcere qui ſit.</l>
                  <l>Nam verae voces tum demùm pectore ab imo</l>
                  <l>Eijciuntur, &amp; eripitur perſona, manet res.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore that be the nature of adverſity and proſperity, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if that be mans nature, ſo to be wrought upon by adverſity and ſo by proſperity; then upon their owne grounds it might eaſily be maintained againſt heathens that croſſes and afflictions in this world, are not effects of <hi>envy</hi> in the ſupreme Diſpenſer of all things, but arguments of his goodneſſe and providence. For what was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more generally received and admired among them, then this divine (ſo they beleeved) praecept or admonition unto men, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon the doores of that famous Church in <hi>Delphus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Know thy ſelfe?</hi> Of which words though many different interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been deviſed by the ancients, (ſo many as would make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113190:27"/>a good large Tractat, if they were all collected into one:) yet that the maine drift and purpoſe of the words was to perſwade men to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Plato</hi> teacheth in his <hi>Charmides;</hi> that is to <hi>humility;</hi> or, <hi>ad minuendam arrogantiam,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> in his Epiſtles <hi>ad Q. Fratrem;</hi> is generally acknowledged. Humility, not towards men onely, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary converſation: but towards God alſo, as in matter of action and religious worſhip, ſo of thoughts and apprehenſions concerning the Deity. Of humility towards God the Latine Lyrick Poet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth well, <hi>Diis te minorem quod geris imperas: Hinc omne principium, huc refer exitum.</hi> and elſewhere againe, <hi>Quantò quiſque ſibiplura ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaverit,</hi> (contrary to the worlds wiſdome, which teacheth men to think highly of themſelves, that others may ſo think of them, and indeed not without ground, among worldly men) <hi>A Diis plura foret.</hi> I know that of old it hath paſſed very current among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that <hi>humility</hi> was altogether unknown unto ancient heathens either Philoſophers, or others, under the notion of a vettue. And well indeed may it be tearmed and deemed the proper vertue of Chriſtians, (or to ſpeake more properly, of the Chirſtian faith) if it be taken in it's full latitude for religious, (or ſpirituall:) for intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall and morall, (or civill) humility: and againe, if it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the vertue of vertues, as by Chriſt our Lawgiver, and his Apoſtles it is propoſed unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and generally acknowledged by all Chriſtians. However, it was not altogether unknowne to heathens as a vertue. The words indeed, <hi>humilis,</hi> and <hi>humilitas</hi> in Latine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Greek, are by them moſt commonly uſed by way of reproach: but even by them as by Chriſtians, in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſenſe ſometimes. Witnes this admirable paſſage of <hi>Plato:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. that is, <hi>God, according to old tradition, having in himſelfe the beginning and the end, and the midſt of all things, in a ſtreight and direct courſe, according to his nature, paſſes on from place to place. And after Him followes alwaies Juſtice, the puniſher of all that forſake the Law of God. Of which whoſoever aspires unto happineſſe, holding faſt, followes with humility and modesty.</hi> (Gr.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113190:27"/>humble and modeſt.) <hi>But he that is puffed up with pride, truſting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in riches or honours, or comelineſſe of body, through youth and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe alſo boyling in himſelfe with arrogancy, as one that needed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther governour nor guide, but able to be a guide unto others; ſuch an one is altogether voide of God.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt here be underſtood ſpiritually, (not metaphyſically;) for what we ſay commonly, void of Gods grace. For otherwiſe, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (ſo is this very place ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Philoponus) De mundo,</hi> teacheth well, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: there doth not, nor can any thing ſubſiſt in the world, altogether void of God. The ſame Author of that exquiſite Treatiſe <hi>De mundo,</hi> who ever he be, (for <hi>Ariſtole's</hi> certainly for divers reaſons, though otherwiſe not unworthy his name, it cannot be) hath the ſame paſſage of <hi>Plato</hi> that we have before, concerning humility, the firſt part of it at the end of his book, and concludes with it: and though he name <hi>Plato,</hi> yet he is miſtaken by many, who referre <hi>Plato's</hi> name, not to theſe words that follow there, but to them that go before, which be not <hi>Plato's.</hi> And whereas in <hi>Plato,</hi> as we ſaw before, it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. there it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which words I know not how to ſave from a direct tautologie, though <hi>Budeus</hi> in his tranſlation hath made a ſhift to avoide it. How the old tranſlator of that Treatiſe <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>letus</hi> found them, becauſe of the liberty he commonly takes, is doubtfull. But however his tranſlation comes much nearer to <hi>Plato's</hi> ſenſe, then that of <hi>Budeus,</hi> or then indeed, (that I may not be thought to lay the fault upon him) the Greek words themſelves, as now printed in that Treatiſe, would bear. I can eaſily believe that the Author of it might alter ſomewhat in <hi>Plato's</hi> words: the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it may be did not pleaſe him: but that he ſhould alter them into meer tautologie, or indeed into <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> I do not believe. <hi>Bonau. Vulcanius,</hi> who hath written lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Commentaries upon this Author <hi>De Mundo,</hi> paſſeth this place over in ſilence, which made me the more willingly to take notice of it.</p>
            <p>But now to return to our word againe; there be others beſides <hi>Plato,</hi> who have uſed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a good ſenſe. <hi>Aemilius Paulus</hi> in <hi>Plut.</hi> having had a great King, whom he had lately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queted and taken, at his feet his humble ſuppliant; and obſerved, it ſeems, among ſome of the younger ſort (brave and gallant ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113190:28"/>otherwiſe, whereof divers of his own kindred) much exultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if not inſultation; preſently retired to his Tent, and having ſent for them, after a long and ſad ſilence, which was much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, he began very pithily and gravely to diſcourſe of the changes of fortune, and inſtability of all humane proſperity, and concluded his diſcourſe with theſe words; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, <hi>Away therefore with your vaine boaſting and bragging for this victory, ô young men, and rather with humility ſtand amazed, and fixing your thoughts altogether upon the future, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with your ſelves with what kinde of unexpected accidents Fortune</hi> [Gr. <hi>Daemon] may requite every one of you hereafter for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proſperity. Antiſtthenes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoret,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, maintained, <hi>that in humility (modeſtia &amp; humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate,</hi> ſo the Latin there: which may alſo be further confirmed by what <hi>Dio. Laertius</hi> writes of him) mans chiefeſt happineſſe conſiſted. In <hi>Plato</hi> but a little before, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I have tranſlated, <hi>humility.</hi> I know the word of it ſelfe admits of other divers inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations; but there I conceived that ſenſe moſt proper. And ſo <hi>Plutarch</hi> I am ſure, ſpeaking of the ſame thing that <hi>Plato</hi> (that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Oracle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) uſeth the word, in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Not to be proud, but humble, is the readieſt way</hi> [Gr. <hi>beſt proviſion] to Philoſophie.</hi> So ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Philo</hi> (of whom a man may almoſt as ſoon learn what <hi>Plato</hi> maintained, as by <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe) in his <hi>De vita contemplat.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which excellent ſaying is thus expreſſed in Latin by S.
<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>Ep.</hi> 56 <hi>ad. Dioſc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine, Ad capeſcendam &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendam veritatem via, prima eſt humilitas, ſecunda humilitas, tertia humilitas.</hi> All which tends to the illuſtration and confirmation of this ſecond reaſon, that if humility be the end of Gods judgements, and in true humility be happineſſe, then thoſe judgements not the effects of <hi>envie,</hi> but of mercy rather.</p>
            <p>There remaineth now nothing but <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> his words of the opinion of many (oppoſed by <hi>Chryſippus</hi>) concerning the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of evils; and the Etymologie of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed) to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>We ſhall begin with <hi>Aulus Gellius,</hi> upon whoſe words if we be long, yet we ſhall not digreſſe from our ſubject. We ſhall ſay little
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113190:28"/>upon him, but we might as well without him, and ſtill keep to our Text. His words then, wherewith be begins his ſixth booke, in ancient editions of <hi>Gellius,</hi> I find thus printed: <hi>Homines feciſſe dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tantam vim eſſe aerumnarum &amp; malorum. Adverſus ea Chryſippus cum in libro</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quarto diſſereret,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So in the <hi>Colon</hi> edition, <hi>Opera &amp; impenſà Ioannis Soteris, Anno</hi> 1526. <hi>menſe Junio.</hi> I know there were many editions of <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> before this; but this is the ancienteſt that I could find at this time. He that took care of it, whether <hi>Soter</hi> or any other, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth (at the end of the two Tables, or <hi>Indices; Ad Lectorem,</hi> &amp;c.) to have compared it with divers former impreſſions, as particularly that which he calls <hi>Veneta impreſſio;</hi> and obſerveth ſome differences of leſſe moment; but not any here: ſo that we may probably ſuppoſe this to have been the reading of ancienter editions alſo. And this the rather becauſe <hi>Petrus Moſellanus</hi> in his Annotations upon <hi>Aul. Gellius,</hi> added to that impreſſion, he alſo is altogether ſilent about it. In another edition by the ſame <hi>Ioannes Soter a. d.</hi> 1533. <hi>menſe Sep.</hi> and another, <hi>Coloniae Agrippinae a. d.</hi> 1563, and another, <hi>Baſileae a.d.</hi> 1565. all which I have lately ſeen, I find no difference, but that in ſome of them, the <hi>dicitur</hi> is parted, or divided from the reſt of the words, with two comma's on each ſide, thus; <hi>Homines feciſſe, dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur, tantam vim eſſe aerumn.</hi> &amp;c. But now, if we come to later editions, in ſome we ſhall find it thus, <hi>Homines feciſſe dicatur: tantam</hi> &amp;c. <hi>dicatur,</hi> for <hi>dicitur,</hi> and a <hi>colon,</hi> or two points, after it. So in the Francford edition, <hi>Ex officanâ Zachario Palthenianâ, a. d.</hi> 1603. much improved by the learned lucubrations (which he calls his <hi>Noctes Pariſinas</hi>) of that great improver of learning, <hi>Henricus Stephanus.</hi> In others, as particularly in that of <hi>Leyden, apud Hieronymum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ogel, a. d.</hi> 1644. it is ſet out as imperfect with three <hi>aſteriſes</hi> (as they call them) at the beginning, thus, * * * <hi>homines feciſſe dicatur: tantam vim eſſe aerumnarum &amp; malorum, adverſus ea Chryſipus,</hi> &amp;c. I hope I ſhall make it appeare cleerely enough that the words before (as in former editions I meane) were very right and full: but what might make ſome men to deem them imperfect, and thereupon, as is moſt probable, raſhly to ſtigmatize them for ſuch, if any deſire my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it is this. Firſt I conceive that they ſtuck at the Latine it ſelf, as either not congruous, or too courſe, to be owned by ſo polite a writer as <hi>Aul. Gellius</hi> is generally acknowledged. Thoſe words of the ſecond period or ſentence, <hi>adverſus ea,</hi> might alſo move them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113190:29"/>as importing (in their conſtruction) much more to have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then that ſhort ſentence. Beſides, they might light upon a Manuſcript (it is very likely they did) that wanted, if not the whole firſt word of the book (as I have ſeen ſome Latine Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts,) yet the firſt letter of the firſt word (then which nothing is more ordinary,) &amp; a void ſpace before it: which was done, where the firſt whether word or letter was intended artificially to be ſet out in colours, and beautified with figures, to be an ornament unto the Book. I have ſeen it in ſome old printed books alſo: as for example, in a <hi>Virgil</hi> and an <hi>Horace</hi> of <hi>Aldus</hi> his Edition, printed <hi>a. d.</hi> 1501. But if either word or letter were for any ſuch reaſon omitted in the ſixth Book, were they not at the beginning of other Books as well, where no ſuch imperfection is noted? They were certainly; but they that ſtuck at this beginning, and did not at others, might unconſiderately phanſie more here, then they did elſewhere. But I will not take upon me to give a reaſon, ſuch an one as may be ſatisfactory, for that which I conceive to have been done without reaſon. However, they that know what inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies, yea, miſchieves ſometimes both to Church and State from ſuch miſtakes have iſſued, will not think ſuch obſervations altogether inconſiderable.</p>
            <p>But now to proceed; whether, as I ſay, it were done without reaſon or no; we ſhall firſt begin with the ſenſe: as for the Latin of the words, we ſhall ſay more of it afterwards. The ſenſe then of thoſe words, <hi>Homines feciſſe dicitur,</hi> &amp;c. I take to be this: That men themſelves were generally ſaid, or ſuppoſed, to have been the cauſe that this world is ſo full of troubles and miſeries. Many, if not moſt ancient Heathens that were of this opinion, did alſo main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that God did not intermeddle with humane affairs. And that which lead them into this conceit, is, becauſe they could not conceive how ſo much wickedneſſe and miſery, as is apparently ſeen and acknowledged among men, could be the fruit of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, who, as he can do no evill himſelfe, ſo he is <hi>of purer eyes then to behold</hi> (with patience &amp; approbation) <hi>iniquity</hi> in others. The Stoick Philoſophers (which Sect <hi>Chryſippus</hi> was a prime, if not ſounder, yet propagator of) ſtood for providence, and a fatall neceſſity of all events; a fatall neceſſity, and yet a freewill too; none more eager and peremptory for it then they. It was indeed the main fundamentall of all their philoſophy. But whileſt they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113190:29"/>went about to reconcile theſe two, how they did involve and puzle themſelves; hath ſufficiently by <hi>Tully</hi> and other Ancients been obſerved. But to this particular of evils, that which they maintained, is, that they partly proceeded from God, and partly from men. From God, and yet he good nevertheleſſe: becauſe, ſaid they, ſuch is the nature of worldly things, that good here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low cannot be without evill. How this buſineſſe is ſtated by <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> and how by <hi>Simplicius,</hi> I muſt refer the Reader to what hath been ſaid of it before: which gave us occaſion to mention this place of <hi>Aul. Gellius.</hi> This, and the next Chapter of this ſixth Book (of the ſaid <hi>Aul. Gellius</hi>) are about it; I mean, concerning the originall of evils, both morall, and others, according to <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus</hi> (anciently famous for the multiplicity of his writings) his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. But I will not meddle with any particulars of the Stoick philoſophy, that are not to our preſent occaſion. So much as hath been ſaid of it was neceſſary for the better underſtanding of theſe words we are now upon. For therefore ſaith <hi>Gellius</hi> that <hi>Chryſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> in his books oppoſed that common opinion.</p>
            <p>That we have next to do, is, to ſhew that ſuch an opinion was, though not approved by all, yet generally known and agitated among ancient Heathens, that men themſelves had been the cauſe of thoſe evils they commonly complained of: And that this was the opinion of ſome, (though not of them only) who either bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly denied the providence; or blaſphemouſly, the goodneſſe of God: which opinion, as commonly known, being here by our Author but briefly ſet down, and not underſtood by ſome that read him, principally, as we conceive, occaſioned this imaginary at the firſt, but now reall (as the words are printed) imperfection. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> ſhall leade, not for his antiquity only, but for his credit alſo among ancient Heathens. In his firſt <hi>Odyſſie</hi> he makes <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf to expoſtulate the matter with mortall men, in theſe words:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſenſe of which words is, That men do wrongfully accuſe the Gods as the authors of their evils, whereas they may thank their own <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wretchedneſſe,</hi> or <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> through which they bring griefs upon themſelves, which never were deſtinated unto them. So the <hi>Golden verſes</hi> (as they commonly call them)
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113190:30"/>containing the chiefe doctrine and inſtructions of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>He ſhall know,</hi> (he that takes a right courſe to knowledge and wiſdome, that is:) <hi>how men by acts of their own free-wils bring miſchiefs upon their own heads,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> an ancient Academick, <hi>Xenocrates</hi> his Scholar, in his Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Hippocles</hi> (cited by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Conſolation to <hi>Apollonius</hi>) had theſe words; [<hi>All theſe things doth that ancient philoſophy well teach and admoniſh; all which if we ſhall not altogether allow of, yet this that concernes the troubles and travels of this life, is certainly true. For if it be not ſo by any order of nature</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are his words) <hi>yet by our ſelves it is brought to this degree of wretchedneſſe and corruption.</hi>] Now theſe, (and ſo divers others whom we may ſpare,) though they derive the chiefeſt miſeries of men from men themſelves, yet doe acknowledge certain <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unavoidable chances,</hi> or <hi>caſualties,</hi> which proceeded from another cauſe; as by <hi>Crantor</hi> his words that follow in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and by other paſſages not of <hi>Homer</hi> only, but even of thoſe <hi>Aurea carmina,</hi> though not many, may appear. The Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ichs might be thought to ſay the ſame; but do not. That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of free-will and fatall neceſſity they ſpeak of, is quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing: as will appear to them that ſhall examine the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the opinions, which we ſhall not now ſtand upon.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Seneca</hi> in his Naturall Queſtions, comes off more roundly, and charges men to the purpoſe. Never did man, I think, (upon one ſingle ſubject, as that is, the benefit of windes) with more wit or Rhetorick plead for providence, then he doth in that Chapter. His words (ſome of them) that chiefly concerne us here, are theſe: <hi>Ingens naturae beneficium, ſi illud in injurtam ſuam non vertat hominum furor, &amp;c. Adeò quicquid ex illis utile &amp; neceſſarium eſt, non poteſt his repenſari, quae in perniciem ſuam generis humani dementia excogitat. Sed non ideò non ſunt naturâ ſuâ bona, ſi vitio malè utentium nocent.</hi> And againe, <hi>Non tamen, ut paulò ante dicebam, queri poſſumus de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore noſtri Deo, ſi beneficia ejus corrumpimus, &amp; ut eſſent contraria ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficimus.</hi> And afterwards more generally yet; <hi>If we ſhall weigh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the benefits of nature by the perverſeneſſe of them that uſe them, we may ſay, we have received nothing but to our hurt. Who uſeth his eyes that he may be the better for them? who his tongue? to whom is not his very life a torment? There is not any thing ſo apparently good and profitable, which abuſe</hi> (or vitiouſneſs) <hi>may not turne to a contrary uſe.</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113190:30"/>Much more to the ſame purpoſe is there to be found.</p>
            <p>Later Philoſophers that have written of this ſubject; to mans wickedneſſe they joyn Gods juſtice, puniſhing or preventing: which how conformable it is to the Scriptures, no Chriſtian need to be told. So <hi>Hierocles</hi> upon the <hi>Aurea Caerminae,</hi> in few words: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Our wickedneſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and Gods righteouſneſſe, theſe two concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring are the cauſe of all our calamities.</hi> It is very well ſaid: but it is not unknown to them that are verſed in theſe Philoſophers that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſince Chriſtianity began to ſpread in the world, that they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, even thoſe that were their greateſt enemies, (as <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> &amp; this very <hi>Hierocles</hi>) divers things from Chriſtians, and ſo might in divers points come nearer to our doctrine then former Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers did. There is not any thing that I more admire in this this kinde then what <hi>Virgil</hi> hath to this purpoſe, in his fourth <hi>Ecloge, Sicelides Muſae, &amp;c.</hi> which (<hi>conſideratis conſiderandis,</hi> what he was, when he lived, &amp;c.) I conceive to be a very good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon GODS words, <hi>Gen.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Aul. Gel.</hi> or rather (for we have not digreſſed) what hath been ſaid, to apply to him; as it often fals out that men may ſpeak the ſame thing, but upon different grounds, and, which much alters a caſe, to contrary ends; ſo we noted before, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who derived the evils and miſeries of this life from men, did it not to maintaine, but to overthrow providence ſo far as in them lay: which muſt now againe be remembred; becauſe to ſuch, eſpecially, theſe words of <hi>Gellius</hi> ſeem to have reference. Thoſe many I ſpeak of were for the moſt part Epicureans; profeſſed Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureans I mean, who poſitively maintained, That God had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to do with the affairs of men, no nor with the World in generall, which they did not acknowledge to have been created by God: and conſequently what either good or evill happened unto men in this World, they muſt needs fetch from ſome other cauſe. <hi>Epicurus</hi> (as <hi>Dio. Laertius</hi> witneſſeth in his life) made this very thing to be the chiefeſt occaſion of evils among men, that men ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the cauſe of their goods &amp; of their evils unto God. So <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of <hi>Epicurus;</hi> ſo <hi>Tully, Plutarch,</hi> &amp; divers others. But the Latin Interpreter of <hi>Diog. Laert.</hi> as if he had ſtudied how to make him ridiculous, and to ſpeak contradictions, he turnes it to a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſenſe, and makes <hi>Epicurus,</hi> of the worſt of Heathens, by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113190:31"/>thens themſelves for his opinions extreamly abhorred, rather a Chriſtian, then a heathen. The ſame <hi>Epicurus,</hi> as the ſame <hi>D. Laer</hi> recordeth, maintained, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. that is, <hi>That moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills men ſuffered (or, were ſubject unto in this life) proceeded from men themſelves; either hatred, or envy, or comtempt being the cauſe.</hi> Upon which foundation, was that famous ſaying of his erected, that <hi>Fortuna ſapienti rarò intervenit,</hi> as his words are tranſlated by <hi>Seneca:</hi> that is, <hi>That Fortune (ſuddaine evill chances and alterations) had little or no power upon a wiſe man:</hi> becauſe he held none wiſe, but ſuch as did altogether ſequeſter themſelves from all ſuch imployments, and courſes of life, as were liable to either hatred or envy. What religion <hi>Pliny</hi> the elder was of, may eaſily be known from himſelfe. It appeares clearely by him, that his religion, in point of doctrine and opinions, was <hi>Epicurus</hi> his religion: and therefore we may probably ſuppoſe that his aime was no other then that of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> where he makes this obſervation, (it is in the <hi>Proem</hi> of his ſeventh book) that <hi>Homini plurima ex homine ſunt mala.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all this that hath been brought from ſeverall authors, of men being the cauſe of evills, well conſidered, let us ſee what there is in <hi>Aul. Gellius</hi> his words juſtly to be excepted againſt, why they ſhould not paſſe for perfect, as in former editions: <hi>Homines feciſſe dicitur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tantam vim eſſe aerumnarum &amp; malorum. Adverſus ea Chryſippus cùm in libro</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quarto diſſereret, Nihil est inquit,</hi> &amp;c. that is, <hi>It is commonly ſaid that men themſelves have bene the cauſe that this world doth ſo abound with evills and miſeries. Againſt which opinion</hi> Chryſippus <hi>in his fourth book of Providence, diſputing, There is nothing, ſaith he,</hi> &amp;c. That this was the opinion of many, hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently been ſhewed, and that <hi>Chryſippus</hi> writing of, and for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, had reaſon to take notice of the opinion, may alſo as clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by what hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>If the Latine of the words were it that they ſtuck at, (a poore buſineſſe to be ſtood upon, when the meaning is knowne) then this happily, <hi>feciſſe tantam eſſe vim,</hi> for, <hi>ut tanta vis eſſet:</hi> which indeed is more ordinary, as <hi>facere ut numerarent,</hi> and <hi>facere ut ſcirent,</hi> in <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Nepos,</hi> and the like: and there is an old Grammarian (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Servius,</hi> or <hi>Priſcian,</hi> I know not well) who ſomewhere paſſeth his judgement, that one <hi>Infinitive</hi> to governe another, is againſt the cuſtome of the Latine tongue: but how much the good man did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſhoot
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113190:31"/>himſelfe in ſo ſaying, let latter accurate Grammarians, (<hi>Alvarez, Voſſius,</hi> and others:) or rather let any ancient Latine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors be looked upon, and it will eaſily appear. If all that is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, may be ſuſpected, that I ſay not condemned, I durſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take out of this one author to produce five hundred places, that may ſeeme more ſtrange then this: ſuch as theſe, <hi>Ibi ſcriptum eſt, tum multa alia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Faceret me, ut earum rerum eſſem prudentior,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Omnia quae pater juſſerit, parendum,</hi> and the like. Or was it, becauſe <hi>adverſus ea,</hi> they thought was improper, after a ſingle ſentence? But if ſo, they ſhould have conſidered that <hi>antea, poſtea, praeterea,</hi> and the like, before that through much uſe they did <hi>coaleſcere</hi> in one word, were ſo taken and uſed divided, as now joyned they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly: <hi>antea,</hi> after one ſingle thing ſpoken of, as well as after many, and ſo of the reſt. I ſay commonly: ſo I take it: though I find that <hi>Hadrianus</hi> the Cardinall in his learned Obſervations, <hi>De ſermone Latino, &amp; modis Latinè loquendi,</hi> dedicated <hi>Carolo Principi Hiſpania<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> makes it a particular obſervation of the word <hi>praeterea: Haec quoque clauſula</hi> (praeterea) <hi>obſervatione praecipuè digna videtur: nam certo modo loquends non poſt multa ſolum connumerata à perfectis illis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus ponitur, verum etiam poſt ſingularem aliquam vel perſonam vel rem. Cicero,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo is <hi>poſtilla</hi> to this day, ſometimes joyned, and ſometimes divided, to be found in <hi>Plautus.</hi> And ſo much to that paſſage of <hi>Aulus Gellius.</hi> we are beholding to him that he gave us the hint of ſo much pertinent matter; and we hope we have in ſome meaſure requited him.</p>
            <p>We are now come to the etymology of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and it is more then reaſon that Grecians themſelves, of whom we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, ſhould be firſt heard about it. <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Cratylus</hi> where he doth purpoſely intreat of the derivation of ancient Greek words, among others, he takes this into his conſideration; and his opinion is, (which hath ſince been followed by moſt,) that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is ſo contracted of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is as much as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wiſe</hi> or <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe there expounds it: or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as <hi>Heſychius,</hi> and the Etymologiſt) that is, <hi>skilfull, well experienced.</hi> And ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we find the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the contrary of it, uſed by <hi>Homer</hi> and others, ſo that of that word or what it ſignifieth, no queſtion at all can be made; though <hi>Plato</hi> mention it, or at leaſt the ſenſe of it, as out of uſe, and in a manner antiquated, in his dayes. And this etymology of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taking it in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113190:32"/>worſt ſenſe for an evill ſpirit, would very well agree with what is written, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 
               <abbr>III</abbr> 1. and elſewhere, of the <hi>ſubtilty of the Serpent.</hi> Some queſtion may be made whether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which would much confirme this derivation) were ever uſed for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some paſſages perchance yet to be found in ancient Greek authors, might induce ſome to beleeve that it hath. As for example this diſtich of the Anthology,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q> Some, to whom the Greek tongue hath been much beholding, produce this very paſſage to prove that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (whereof much hath been ſaid before) is ſometimes taken for <hi>cacodaemon,</hi> that is, <hi>a devill,</hi> Whether they were led into this error by thoſe that firſt wrote upon thoſe Epigrams, or led them into it, I know not: but an error it is, as will eaſily appeare to any that ſhall wel examine the conſtruction of the words, which cannot ſtand with that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: neither is the jeſt or <hi>acumen</hi> of them any wayes improved by it, but rather obſcured and impaired. I did wonder, ſaith the Poet, to ſee a black <hi>Maure</hi> Profeſſor of Rhetorick; ſuch eloquence from ſuch lips, (in another Epigram to the very ſame purpoſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>triple lips</hi>) to proceed, ſo white an attire, (ſuch was the cuſtome of thoſe times) upon ſo black a skin. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore here muſt of neceſſity be tranſlated either <hi>peritus,</hi> or <hi>Deus:</hi> but the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being not onely more warrantable, becauſe common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; but alſo, (in that ſenſe that <hi>Tully</hi> calls <hi>Plato, Deum philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiae</hi>) farre more emphaticall here, is doubtleſſe to be preferred: and ſo indeed I find the word by ſome others that have written upon the ſame Epigrams well rendred.</p>
            <p>And ſo much I had to ſay concerning this Etymology, which makes the word originally a Greek word. Others there be of the ſame kinde, mentioned by Greek Grammarians, and others, but obvious enough, and in my judgement ſo little conſiderable, that I thinke it needleſſe to inſiſt upon them here. Neither indeed would I eagerly contend with any man about this matter, the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the word in generall, whether Greek or Hebrew, but that it may be lawfull for any man to beleeve what himſelfe ſhall thinke beſt about it. Nevertheleſſe, becauſe it is generally agreed upon by the learned that are skilfull in the tongues, (whereof I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake more at large in a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113190:32"/>ſhortly, God willing, to publiſh, <hi>concerning languages,</hi>) that moſt ancient Greek words, the ſacred eſpecially, came original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Hebrew, (the Mother of all ancient Tongues) and thence ought to be fetcht; I doubt I ſhould not give the learned Reader that ſatisfaction that he may perchance expect from me, ſhould I not take notice of what hath been ſaid by others to this purpoſe concerning this word; and alſo impart unto him what I can ſay my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I have read ſomewhere (in <hi>Lilius Gyraldus,</hi> as I remember) that <hi>Steuchus Eugubinus,</hi> a man well verſed in this kinde of learning, did fetch this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by an <hi>Aphereſis</hi> of the firſt ſyllable, from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Devils:</hi> which muſt be upon a ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at the firſt was taken in the worſt ſenſe. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>God,</hi> he would rather upon the ſame grounds have ſaid from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, <hi>God,</hi> often uſed in the Scriptures. There be examples I know (in all languages, ſome) of ſuch <hi>aphere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> or contractions of words: and what other conſiderations <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gubinus</hi> might have beſides to perſwade him, I know not, becauſe I have him not at this time, nor indeed know certainly in which of his Books to ſeek it. <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> that incomparable man, in his Annotations upon the New Teſtament is of opinion that the word is <hi>ex Arabicâ Origine</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> probably, which ſignifies <hi>to endure</hi> and <hi>continue:</hi> a fit word to expreſſe Gods eternity, then which nothing is more proper unto him, and in that reſpect a plauſible derivation. But that any ſuch word as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to expreſſe either <hi>God</hi> or a <hi>good Spirit</hi> (which his words ſeem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) is uſed in that tongue, is more then I can yet learne, though I have done my beſt to ſatisfie my ſelfe. Neither in <hi>Herodotus</hi> or any other ancient Author that mentions the Deities anciently worſhipped by the <hi>Arabs,</hi> doe I finde any thing that approacheth to it. <hi>Ludovicus Vartomannus</hi> indeed (cited by Mr. <hi>Voſſius,</hi> in his firſt. <hi>De Origine Idolol. cap.</hi> 8.) in his Navigations relateth that the <hi>Calecutenſes</hi> call the Devill <hi>Deumum,</hi> which comes ſomewhat near; but what affinity their tongue hath with the <hi>Arabick,</hi> or of what antiquity that appellation with them is, I know not. <hi>Petrus Texera</hi> in his <hi>Relationes,</hi> as he cals them, of the Kings of <hi>Perſia, lib.</hi> l <hi>c.</hi> 5. witneſſeth that the <hi>Perſians,</hi> beſides other names, call the Devill, <hi>Diu;</hi> which comes near (and probably came from it) to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113190:33"/>the <hi>Syriack,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as ſome write it, which ſignifies not <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> but <hi>Daemoniacus</hi>) but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as in the <hi>Syriack</hi> Tranſlation of the New Teſt, it often doth occurre. Somewhat here might be ſaid of the Latin <hi>Deus,</hi> and the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, alſo: but I will keep me to my task, the etymologie of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which for thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have been intimated, I would rather derive from the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, then Arabick. And becauſe I cannot pitch upon any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular with any warrantable certainty, I ſhall therefore propoſe to the Reader ſome variety, that he may have ſome choice and pleaſe himſelf.</p>
            <p>If then neither that of <hi>Eugubinus,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; nor what we have intimated of the Syriack <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be allowed, I would have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſanguis,</hi> taken into conſideration, becauſe moſt of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties worſhipped by ancient Heathens, were obſerved, (a ſubject much inſiſted upon by ancient Fathers) or at leaſt beleeved gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to delight in the blood both of Men and Beaſts: or rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſimilem eſſe,</hi> from whence come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Chaldaik</hi> words, ſignifying, <hi>ſhapes, figures, images,</hi> and the like. And among theſe ſhould I reckon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(ſit honos auribus:) ſtercus, &amp;c.</hi> the ſame reaſon might be given for it as is commonly (and is as currently received) for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Idols,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame ſignification as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I doubt my Reader by this hath enough, and perchance he thinks more then enough of this ſtuffe. Yet I will crave leave that I may touch upon one etymon more, becauſe it will give us occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to impart ſomewhat that is not vulgarly known, nor imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to our maine ſubject. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Hebrew, a very common word, ordinarily ſignifies, <hi>to keep ſilence:</hi> from whence alſo proceed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taken for a <hi>Sepulchre</hi> ſometimes in the Hebrew: and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the very ſame word) the name of a certain Angell of death (as they call him) in the Chaldy Dialect. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alone, as it ſignifies <hi>ſilere,</hi> would excellently well fit (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Heſiod,</hi> being often taken for the ſame) an obſervation of <hi>Heſychius</hi> concerning the <hi>Heroes;</hi> which is this: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The better,</hi> (or, <hi>excelling.) So do they call the Heroes, who ſeem to be a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous kinde. Whence it is that thoſe that paſſe by the Heroa,</hi> (or, <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples conſecrated to the Heroes;</hi> or, <hi>any Heroes) uſe to keep ſilence, leſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113190:33"/>they be hurt by them. So</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is,) <hi>are alſo the Gods called, as by</hi> Aeſchylus <hi>in his Aetna.</hi> The ſame obſervation is in the <hi>Sholiast.</hi> upon <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and a pregnant paſſage of <hi>Menander</hi> concerning the miſchievouſneſſe of theſe <hi>Heroes</hi> (beſides <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> his own words about it) is there alſo. In <hi>Euſtathius</hi> alſo upon the ſecond <hi>Iliad,</hi> but more imperfectly, it is to be found. I will make no further application my ſelfe, but having now done my part, as I conceive, concerning the etymon of this word, leave all to the Reader, as his own judgement, or phancy ſhall incline him.</p>
            <p>I remember ſomewhat concerning ſome other words (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) was promiſed and referred to this place. Of the firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all that I intended about it, was my opinion only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the right etymon of it, which becauſe I hope to have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opportunity for it elſewhere, and would not be overlong here upon that argument of Etymologies, I ſhall now forbear. As for the ſecond, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I have ſince found ſo much already obſerved of it by others, as namely by <hi>Henry Stephen,</hi> partly in his <hi>Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> (a Book well known to all that aſpire to any perfection in the Greek tongue) and partly in his learned Animadverſions upon <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his <hi>Adagies,</hi> that I ſhall but need to refer my Reader to him: this only briefly added, That whereas he quoteth ſome ancient Grammatians and others, concerning the etymon of it, it ſeemeth farre more probable to me, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>vehemens Dea,</hi> as the Poet <hi>Catullus</hi> ſpeaketh of it: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the puniſher of overſwelling, unbridled,</hi> whether ſpeeches or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the Grecians) is a pure Hebrew word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; from whence comes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the ſame difference of <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> (the one <hi>aſpirat,</hi> the other <hi>lenis</hi>) being in the Hebrew, as well as in the Greek words.</p>
            <p>The laſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: this alſo, (and ſo acknowledged by all men) a pure Hebrew word: but that is not it that I would ſay of it. It is ſometimes taken for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the envie of the Daemon:</hi> which I think few men have obſerved. As for example, in <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi> upon a very obſervable occaſion, the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtians among themſelves, by both Jewes and Gentiles (as <hi>Clemens</hi> there witneſſeth) objected to Primitive Chriſtians, as a main argument againſt their faith. Among other things that are anſwered by him, he hath theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113190:34"/>which words are rendred by the Latin Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, <hi>Hujus aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m couſa quod quicquid eſt pulchrum ſequitur reprehenſio.</hi> He had need to be very ſagacious, if not a very <hi>Oedipus,</hi> that ſhall underſtand <hi>Clemens</hi> by theſe Latin words. His purpoſe was to anſwer them according to their own principles, who upon all occaſions (as before we have ſhewed) of any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary either felicity, or excellency in any kinde had this ſtill <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the envie of the Daemon,</hi> in their mouthes, and the dread of it in their hearts. And indeed the very word uſed by other ancient Chriſtians, Hiſtorians, and others, upon this, or the like occaſion (as the peace of the Church diſturbed by perſecutions) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> in his 21 Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the praiſe of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>This peace and proſperity of Gods Church, envy</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>could not end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</hi> Where it is apparent by the words immediately following, that by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>envie,</hi> muſt be underſtood <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or (he being a Chriſtian) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the envie of the Devill:</hi> So <hi>Euſebius,</hi> but more fully, after he had ſpoken of the peace and tranquillity of the Church for many years: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Theſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no envie did restraine, no evill Daemon either by faſcination, or any plots and machinations of men was able to hinder, &amp;c.</hi> In which words, what at the firſt is briefly contained in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>envie,</hi> is afterwards more fully declared and expreſſed in the words following; as will yet more clearly appeare to them that ſhall obſerve many ſuch expreſſions of ancient Fathers upon other ſubjects alſo, where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>envie,</hi> will not admit of any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</p>
            <p>Neither will it be wondred that <hi>Momus,</hi> in <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> or any where elſe ſhould be taken for an envious and ſpightfull <hi>Daemon,</hi> if it be remembred that according to ancient mythologie, <hi>Momus</hi> was he that gave that pernicious counſell to <hi>Jupiter</hi> againſt mankinde, to caſt the ſeeds of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and diſſentions among men, that they might deſtroy one another <hi>(Neque hic lupis mos, nec fuit leonibus Vnquam, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi in diſpar, feris:)</hi> by warres and mutuall ſlaughters. It is ſaid (ſo I finde it in <hi>Euſtathius</hi> upon the firſt of <hi>Homers Iliads</hi>)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113190:34"/>that he did it to ſave the earth from a generall deluge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration, which <hi>Jupiter</hi> was about; hee ſuggeſting to him, that this would be a more plauſible and <hi>methodicall</hi> way, and offering himſelfe to contrive the buſineſſe for him. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry likely that what we reade in <hi>Geneſis</hi> of the confuſion of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and ſcattering of men (before knitted and united in <hi>one Speech</hi> and <hi>one Language,</hi> as is expreſly noted, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 
               <abbr>XI.</abbr> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 1.) upon the face of the Earth, might be the firſt occaſion of this Fable. But I have not further to do with that here. If I have done (in any reaſonable proportion) what I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, I am glad, and heartily ſay,</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Na. Brent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="passages">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:113190:35"/>
            <head>Some Paſſages of Authors before mentioned, and, here at the end, promiſed.</head>
            <p>¶ See before Page 4.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> in Phaed.</bibl> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Joach. Camerarius, <hi>Elem. Rhetor.</hi> cap. <hi>De Fabulis,</hi> p. 36.</bibl> 
               <hi>Quo tempore exacto Saturno at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pulſo coeleſtibus regnis, Juppiter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium conſtituere ac ordinare coeperat, affuere coram illo voluptaſque &amp; dolor cum graviſſimis criminibus &amp; poſtulationibus, quibus ſe mutuo inceſſebant. Jupiter ratus è re maxime eſſe &amp; ſua &amp; rei publ. inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia &amp; odia deleri, operam dedit ut diſſenſionem litigantium componeret, &amp; gratiam inter illos conciliaret. Sed frustrà expertus omnia, tandem renitentes &amp; invitos vinculis inſolubilibus aſtrinxit at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> colligavit, ut quamvis diſſiderent, unà tamen perpetuò at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimul traherentur, &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſi tu, &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Page 5.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Herodotus, <hi>in Tbalia,</hi> ſive <hi>lib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>III.</abbr> 
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 40.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:113190:35"/>
            <p>¶ Page 8.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Homerus <hi>Il.</hi> Ω vel, <hi>uit.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<note place="margin">1. Alii, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ita &amp; <hi>Plut.</hi> in <hi>Conſol. ad Apol.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Plato <hi>De Republ. lib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>II.</abbr>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Page 27. and 35.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ariſtoteles <hi>Metaphyſ. lib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>I.</abbr> 
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</bibl> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:113190:36"/>
            <p>¶ Page 39.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſid. Peluſ. <hi>Epiſt. lib.</hi> 
                  <abbr>II.</abbr> 
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 74. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113190:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
